Hey Beth!
Hey Erin! Lovely to see you as always.
You too!
Welcome everyone to another episode of Ask Erin, Dear Beth, where we talk through your
common image analysis problems and try to teach you how we do stuff and how we make our own
lives easier and hopefully make your lives easier as well.
Welcome to the docket for today!
Yeah, so today we're going to take a look at some images that are in proprietary file
formats.
So some microscopes just give you things like a TIP file or even a JPEG files that you're
used to seeing, files that maybe come off the digital camera that you have or your phone's
camera.
Some microscopes don't do that.
Some microscopes make these proprietary file formats that are specific to that microscope.
And they can be a little bit scary if you don't know how to handle them.
So we're going to actually look at doing two different things with these file formats today.
One of them is putting them in image.js and actually just turning them into TIFs that
are then more portable and easier to move around.
And the other one is actually using the same library that image.js uses a library called
Bioformats to read those directly into CellProfiler and then you can skip that intermediate
step where you're making copies of the data.
Nice.
All right.
Shall we do it?
Let's do it.
All right.
So here I have two files.
These are proprietary files that are called dot flex that have come off a microscope.
And I got this data from the IDR.
If you check out our episode on downloading data from the IDR, these are the data that
we downloaded.
And we love using public data wherever we can because it's great.
People have said that they want to share it and it's usually also really good, really
clean data.
People tend not to share their absolute ugliest data.
Maybe they should.
Nobody wants to show off their dirty laundry.
So here we have two wells.
So this is well H10 and this is well J9 from one particular plate of data.
And the reason I'm showing first that opening this in image.js is because that is always
what I do when I get new data.
I don't know about you, Erin, but the very first thing I do when I get new data is I
just go to Image.js because Image.js is wonderful.
It is lovely.
It is so great.
And I never really want to do anything else.
Yeah.
I mean, I think that is so many good principles there.
First thing you do when you get any data is look at it.
We are biologists at heart and we want to see the pictures first.
And then yeah, Image.js is a very usable tool for looking at images.
So here we are looking at images.
So we can see some of the metadata which Image.js has so helpfully loaded for us.
And it says that we have four channels here and 20 time points.
I also have some like random metadata has been added here by the microscope manufacturer.
And I was surprised.
I kind of thought that this was going to then change into field number, whatever, because
these are clearly not actually different time points.
These are clearly different sites in the world, but sometimes metadata reading is not perfect.
Yeah.
So even one of the challenges of proprietary file format, I mean of any file format that
has metadata saved into it, like here Bioformats is doing its very best to parse the metadata.
But as biologists with some level of intuition, again, like we can't rely strictly on what
the computer can do for us.
It's doing its best.
It tried.
It found 28 different things.
But we have a level of intuition here where we can say, well, actually, I can look at those
and tell you that those, you know, each image is too disparate from the one next to it.
Those are clearly not the same cells imaged over time.
Those are clearly different, you know, images of different cells.
And so maybe that doesn't actually matter for your experiment.
Like whatever, you know, whatever it's parsing, as long as it says there's 28 different things
you can just proceed with there.
But sometimes it does matter, you know, how it's parsing, parsing different bits of metadata.
So that's just something to keep in mind, to like to double check it and change it if
you need to.
And if you don't, don't worry about it, but a good thing just to keep in mind.
And this is pretty common.
A lot of programs for doing microscopy image analysis assume that there are five dimensions
XYZ channel and time.
They don't really take into account multiple fields of view, because it's not really something
you would usually look at in a single file, except for that those are easier to port around.
And so this is a really common mistake in that there was only one dimension left.
And so it used it for that.
So here I've opened up my channels tool.
These are also the things that I always do when I have new data is I go to image, color,
I do the channels tool.
And then I also go to image, adjust brightness contrast.
And with those two windows open, you can do just about anything.
So I'm going to change this from grayscale to composite max so I can see all of my channels
out once.
And because it's going to automatically min max the data, I'm going to then also just
go through and hit this auto button here, you know, it's blowing out some of the channels,
but I'm just trying to really get a sense of what's going on in this data.
And so we clearly have a cytoskeletal marker here in this fourth channel.
This first channel is some sort of a nuclear marker.
And we could go back and we could look at the metadata that the people have uploaded
in order to sort of, if we needed to know more specifically than that, but for our purposes
here, we're just kind of exploring and seeing what's going on.
Some sort of cytosolic marker.
And some marker that I'm not quite sure what it is.
It's really bright here.
It's really bright here in some of these speckly places.
So those could be debris or those could be mitosis that could be like some sort of a
mitotic marker.
And this is from the same plate.
So it should hopefully have all the same channels, but we can convince ourselves that what's
how similar the data is or is not going to be when we then actually start trying to do
our analysis again by just doing the same thing.
And we could even transfer the settings if we wanted across from one to the other.
But here again, we're just going for vibes.
Yeah.
And I think an important thing to point out here is we're not changing the data, the underlying
data itself.
Super important point.
What we're doing is just changing how it is being shown to our eyes.
So, you know, our eyes can see now clearly the patterns that are happening in these cells,
but the underlying data has not been changed by adjusting this right here.
Yeah, absolutely.
I can change it if I want.
If I hit this apply button, it will apply it, but it will warn me before I do that.
But I don't want to do that because again, we're really just trying to get a sense of
our data here.
So there's nothing wrong with having data in this format, but if for whatever reason,
I was dealing with something downstream where I didn't want the data in this format either
because I don't want it in the dot flex proprietary format, which requires a special reader, imagery
and CellProfiler, I both use bio formats, which is an open source thing for doing reading.
But for whatever reason, you didn't want to deal with that.
Or if just you wanted to not have the data broken one thing per well, maybe you just
want to send one site of images.
And so you don't actually want that big of a data.
You just want everything by itself.
What you can actually do is go to file, save as image sequence.
And that will actually let you then say, all right, I need I want a two digit number or
a three digit number here, but you could change the number of digits for like channel time
point should make everything be at least two digits.
Because you know, for one thing I have 28.
So if I try to make that one digit, I expect Fiji will yell at me, but I usually try not
to make Fiji mad if I can avoid it.
And so that is just going to then very quickly fill that folder up.
And so we have our original image, which is this string here that indicates that we're
in well Jane nine.
We have time point zero zero one and we have channel zero zero one and so on and so forth.
So I'm just going to quickly do the same thing.
It's not export it's save as.
And I'm going to put my data in the right place because staying organized is nice.
Look at that.
Yeah.
So, Beth, I before we leave Fiji, I've got one question when you very first like opened
up those images, you drag and you just dragged and dropped them to the toolbar and something
popped up when you did that.
Yeah.
Great thing that I completely breezed over.
So this is the bioformat loader.
So that's actually how you know that this is using bioformats to load that data.
And again, bioformats fantastic open source project, you know, that is adds incredible
value to the community.
And it gives you a lot of different options.
If you want, you could say that you only want you want each thing with its own channel
or its own time point.
So if I wanted all of those files individual, I wanted like each thing I could do that.
I can also ask it to show me some of the metadata, Erin's favorite thing metadata.
If there were ROI's that had been saved off of your microscope or when you saved the data
last, you could open those.
So a lot of things you can do with the bioformats loader.
But that is showing you that it's not just sort of opening a random image, it's opening
an image using bioformats and Fiji is really smart about it will usually try to open things
with a regular loader.
And then if it can't, it'll ask bioformats like, Hey, can you handle this data?
And bioformats can handle hundreds of different kinds of file formats.
It's so great.
Awesome.
So you didn't, when you opened up these images, you didn't change anything away from default.
Nope.
I just left everything exactly the same.
You write that like I could have, I could have since I've eventually put everything
into composite, I could have moved everything into composite, or I could have sort of changed
some things about the order or again, split out the channels and things.
But it's nice to just keep one file, one sort of window per well, and then be able to sort
of scroll back and forth.
Awesome.
Great.
Thank you for pointing that out that I totally missed that.
Cool.
So what happens when you want to put this data into CellProfiler?
So sub profiler, like I said, also uses bioformats.
So it can actually open those dot flex files.
And it's pretty simple, but because it's often a little bit easier to do it with individual
files, at least in sort of walking you through how CellProfiler it's open data, I'm going
to actually start from these individual files that we've made.
So here I've dragged and dropped these in.
We now have all of our individual things.
I can click on each one.
And there's our channel one, our nuclei, channel two, our sort of marker that we said was kind
of cytosolic, but we weren't quite sure.
This is the one we said might be mitotic, and this is the one that we said was definitely
cytoskeletal.
So if I wanted to say load just the nuclear and the cytoskeletal ones just so that I
could get a quick sense of like I want to identify cells, this is what I would do.
I've loaded all of my data.
I know the way that it's telling the difference between the different channels.
It's with the C thing that we told image J to make.
So if I go to my names and types module, all I need to do in order to tell names and types
what my different channels are is I can say if a file has C001 in it, it's a DNA image.
So I change this from all images to images matching rules because we have multiple kinds
of images here.
And then I can say add another image and I can say if it has C004 in it that this is
our cytoskeletal.
If I hit update, what will hopefully happen here is I will now see we had 28 sites per
well and we did two wells.
So I will hopefully get a message from CellProfiler here that is giving me 56 image sets.
Let's find out.
56 image sets.
So I've only loaded those two channels here.
If I wanted to load more channels, I could just keep hitting add more images and add
in our other images.
But all I had to do was figure out what is the thing that makes that channel unique.
And so allow that to be a moment where we plug for the importance of having a consistent
naming structure for your data.
So if you have a naming structure, doing a step like this where you say, hey CellProfiler,
the way you can tell which images are my DNA marker and which are my cytoskeletal is just
by looking for this in the file name, your life will get a lot simpler.
If your files all are named slightly differently, you're going to have a much harder time.
Yeah.
And this is something that we, like, we help teach collaborators sort of all the time.
I think, especially as we are in the more computational realm, I think biologists who
don't have computational training and who are used to perhaps just opening up every
picture and looking by eye and writing down notes.
Even if you're in the early stages of data exploration, data generation, it doesn't matter
so much.
And so it's not something that you're used to thinking about.
But as you move into the realm of computation, the realm of reproducible analyses, that is
sort of a frame shift is required in thinking about it.
We're like, oh, actually, when I've got handfuls of images and I'm doing stuff by hand, it
doesn't really matter.
But when you start to scale and when you start to do things where a computer is parsing things
instead of you going and clicking on your files, then it really does actually start
to matter a lot.
And this is something that we help teach collaborators moving into this space all the time.
And in the defense of biologists, including both you and me, Erin, this is not something
that was generally, I didn't learn, you know, get to grad school day one, like file naming
structures.
I wish.
I wish that was what had happened.
But totally it was not what happened.
I mean, I'm sure that when I first got trained at the microscope, they were like, you should
have consistent file naming, but I didn't understand why it mattered.
And once you start doing this, then you understand why it mattered.
And then you wish you'd started doing it a year or two before.
Absolutely.
No, I mean, you know, as Beth said, like she and I are both wet lab biology trained before
moving into this space.
So these are all lessons that we learned the hard way.
We would like you to learn the easy way.
Yeah.
All right.
So what if I hadn't split these things apart?
What if I had kept them all together?
I'm going to clear file list, such a useful thing in CellProfiler.
And instead, I'm going to drag in these files.
I'm now going to have to do one extra step that I completely skipped when I was doing
everything being an individual file, which is I'm going to have to extract metadata.
Now, this is one of the modules in CellProfiler that people find the scariest and I don't blame
them because when it first comes up, it shows you all of this horrible regular expression
stuff, which is about trying to get information from the file name.
So if, especially if you use a high content microscope, where you're generating scans
of a plate, you will, you might have something where things like the well position are encoded
in your file name.
That's in fact, exactly what we have here.
But if you're not used to looking at computers, this is horrifying.
And in fact, probably the thing you will use more often, certainly if you have proprietary
file formats is this extract from image file headers.
So what this is saying is, hey, we know that there's a whole bunch of files in here.
In fact, we know from opening these in Fiji, there's 112 files in each file.
So probably could you just go look at that and, you know, figure that out for me.
So I hit the extract button.
And I hit update and hurray.
So profiler has in fact found it for me.
So it's showing here that my four channels, I have now learned something about when
this experiment was done.
There are apparently three cameras on this microscope.
And for the first exposure, they used cameras one and three.
And the second and third, they used camera two.
That's pretty cool.
And we have lots of information that was encoded in the metadata.
So profiler doesn't pull every piece of metadata, but it pulls a bunch of them.
And we have our same well information that we had over an image.
Shay.
And we have our four channels and our 20 time points.
So we got the exact same answer either way, which is what we hope.
Because we're using the same software under the hood.
So that's all well and good.
But so profiler before was using the file names to sort of tell the difference
between the channels.
So we're going to have to do something different here.
So the things that are different between the channels, if we just look at what
metadata we have, are this C and this channel name.
C goes zero one, two, three.
So profiler is written in Python, which is what's called a zero counted language.
It doesn't count one, two, three, four.
It counts zero, one, two, three.
I'm sure there's a reason I don't know what it is, but that's how they decided to do it.
So I could use this zero, one, two, three, or I could use these different channel names.
I know me.
I will have a harder time remembering these.
So I'm going to use this C parameter instead.
But I could have used the other one if this had been named something like
nuclei and cytoskeleton.
It would have been easy for me to remember.
I could do that too.
So all I need to do when I go over to the names and types modules now, it's not based on file anymore.
It's based on metadata.
So I just click that file that drop down next to file and I click metadata.
And it actually defaults to asking, is it C that you want to use?
Because that is the thing that people most commonly want to use for channel.
And I'm going to tell it I want zero, which is our previous one.
And instead of four here, I'm going to have to change it to three, because again,
we're changing counting schemes.
But now again, hopefully I hit update and I continue to have 56.
We still do.
And so we've now taught cell par filer in a couple of different ways,
how to open these proprietary file formats with different metadata structures.
We've explored them with ImageShay.
And now we would be ready to actually build our pipeline and do a real experiment.
Awesome.
Look at that.
Good to go.
It felt a little scary at first, but once you kind of understand like
CellProfilers internal logic, we got through it.
It's not so bad.
Definitely not so bad.
And I love the thing about, you know, just made me think here where you're saying like,
oh, we've got a, you know, a default of C matching, like a sort of a big picture thing
about CellProfiler is, you know, it is biologists, us biologists that are heavily
involved in the creation and maintenance and, you know, updating of CellProfiler.
And so all of these defaults that you find within CellProfiler all over the place
are actually considered, you know, we have very opinionated biologists in our team,
you know, and, and we weigh in very much.
I'm like, Hey, actually, this is what I, you know, this is what I think is the most
common. This is what I'm encountering all the time.
This is so my collaborators are encountering all the time.
And so, you know, the default things throughout CellProfiler are actually, you know, even
if they're not what you want necessarily, they're often pretty informative about sort
of a way of thinking about any given thing that like this is the most common use case
for whatever you're filling in that has a default.
In defense of CellProfiler.
In defense of opinionated biologists.
I think that's that's we certainly defend and support those wherever we can.
Absolutely.
All right. Well, thank you so much for joining us.
Hope this helped.
See you next time.
Bye.