Hey Beth, hello.
Okay, so bonus episode time.
We are not going to talk science because we are nerds of many interests.
Many shared nerderies.
Many shared nerderies between us.
Yeah, so we thought we could chat for a minute about a different shared nerdery that is Great
British Baking Show or Bake Off.
We're getting a new season soon.
So soon, as in like this week.
Yeah, so probably even by the time I get this posted, it will have already started because
I think the first episode already aired in Britain and then it's a few days later before
it airs here.
So yeah, we are like we are right at the start of what is the season 15?
What season is this?
I don't know.
Yeah.
16, I think.
I think that's yeah.
I think it's probably 16.
That's a lot of bake-offs.
Okay, so for those that are not in the know, I suppose, I mean probably people are, if
they're not in the know, they're like, oh, I don't want to watch this episode, right?
But like for anybody that doesn't know, there's been the Great British Bake Off, also known
as GBBO, that is a reality show that is from Britain, as one might expect by the name,
a pretty competition where the bakers compete, you know, like any sort of generic competition
show like starts with a big group and each week, you know, they drop another person until
you get to the end and there's a winner and they're competing by baking, which, okay,
sure.
So let's go into like why we love that.
I think, okay, yes, you and I both like to bake and we can nerd out about that too, but
I think the thing for me, like I am not into reality TV at all.
Like I don't watch much TV to begin with because I have 400 things that I've, you know, there's
always like too many things to do.
So it never quite makes it to the top of my, anyway, that's a whole other thing.
The thing is, I know, I know, get me chatting and I'm like not able to follow a single conversational
path.
The thing I love about Bake Off the Most though is just how kind the people are on the show.
Right?
Like it may be a competition, but you have, but like very regularly, especially when you
get into a season when they like really get to know each other and become good friends,
like it's not just the person leaves that's crying.
It's like they announced somebody's leaving.
I'm like, everybody starts crying because they're like, no, I was like, I love you and
support you and you're a delight and a friend.
I feel like with Bake Off they are there to make friends.
Yes, absolutely.
Like the opposite of normal reality TV.
Yeah.
So that is, I think, a huge reason.
I love it and a huge reason why, yeah, why I am perpetually drawn back to it and can
even go and like rewatch old seasons.
It's like it's not about who wins.
I also like learning about sweets and all sorts of things that I like very much have
never heard of and be like, ooh, that's a cool thing.
Maybe I will try to make that someday.
Yes.
Yeah, I have definitely learned a lot about baking by watching Bake Off in part, especially
like the last several years because we've got kind of a crazy thing in my family around
Bake Off.
So a chunk of my family, well, so I'll say like this didn't seem, okay, there's a chunk
of my family that's like super into sports and many of them do sports, fantasy leagues.
They watch sports of all kinds together.
I mean, I even have a family member who was a professional athlete.
Like lots of sports going on.
That didn't, I didn't inherit that.
I am not a sports person, but that's like where the idea got started of having a fantasy
Bake Off league.
So my family, what?
Yes.
So my family every year now for a number of years, we have drafted, had a draft where
we each get to pick to bake off.
You know, it's like it's a whole sports draft.
We have a commissioner.
Zachary is the commissioner.
You know, commissioner Zachary, he handles, you know, handles the rules and the drafting,
Tally's points.
And we each end up- Is it always the same commissioner?
Yes.
No, it's, it all is always commissioners that because nobody, nobody can do better than
he can.
Zach, and he sends, oh my gosh, like the best emails.
He's so witty, like, you know, adore Zach and appreciate him so much for his efforts
in our Bake Off league.
So we, you know, we do a family draft.
In fact, ours is tonight after dinner.
We're all getting on Zoom and doing the draft.
And so each team gets to pick two bakers.
And then there's points given every week based on how long they stay in the show.
So each episode, there's like more points.
If somebody gets a Hollywood handshake, there's bonus points.
If they get star baker, if they win the technical challenge.
And we track those points and there's the winner at the end.
The funny thing is, I think Stephen and Maria have won every single time.
And they're perhaps the least bakery of the like households, but the most sporty of the
household.
So somehow their like sports knowledge seems to-
They've drafted in other things.
I don't know.
I don't understand why Stephen and Maria are able to win every year in the draft, but
they do and I adore them for it.
Because they probably are, yes, bake.
Is there a prize?
Would you win something?
Yeah.
And we have an engraved platter of family Bake Off winner.
No, it's a full thing.
And there is also, we have a spirit points competition, which has changed slightly in
how we calculate the points over the years.
I like how we did it originally because I always won.
Well, of course.
You know, of course.
That's not the like.
Yeah.
Well, so actually, so the first couple of years I won kind of hands down because I work
from home.
My office is in my basement.
So it was very easy for me.
Like I get up early in the morning with my daughter, I get dough going or, you know, whatever.
And then like, since I'm at home, I can just like pop up in between meetings and like,
oh, I need to need my dough.
Like, oh, so this actually involves baking.
So the spirit points is about baking.
Yeah.
So you get points for baking during each week.
Initially it was just like baking.
You got bonus points if you baked the technical.
So I have actually baked many of the technical recipes from the last several years of bake
off, if not most of them.
I have to say, you know, including you and I one time got you got the ingredients.
I was visiting Boston and we were all set to bake the pithivier.
I will always remember.
I'm not even talking to find a pithivier, but it was like a pithivier.
And we were all set to bake it at the hotel, you know, staying in like one of the hotels
with kitchenettes until we then realized that we couldn't actually do that during our work
day because it didn't have an oven, just a cooktop and a microwave.
Yes.
Note to folks who live in the Pacific Northwest, Aaron has a lot of baked goods.
And this is a good friend to have.
Yes.
So, OK, so it was just based on like, you know, how much you baked, but then a couple
plot twists in the, you know, in things.
So I was the only person working from home.
You know, I have family, like one household, they're both lawyers, like not an option to
move dough around during the day.
Other households, like teachers also not an option to like be at home and like, you know,
do in and out of the oven between meetings.
Then there was the year that my aunt Deborah retired and then it was a heated race between
me and her because once she retired, she had a heck of a lot more time to bake and was home.
And so then heated race, I think she won that year, you know, begrudgingly excited for her
because I was glad she got to retire.
And then we have since shifted now to sort of even the playing field for those that do
not work from home and or are retired.
Spirit points are based on, you know, you get a point for baking that week, anything.
You can get an extra point if it is on theme.
So it doesn't have to be the technical recipe.
It just needs to be like on theme for the week.
And in part, the driving decision behind that was concordant with the third point you can get
for baking gluten free because in the middle of our family's obsession with bake off, four of my
family members were diagnosed as celiac.
And that's a problem.
Yeah.
So making it impossible to follow most of the technical recipes and and for those that are not
major bakers like gluten.
So celiac is an allergy to gluten and gluten is a huge, huge.
It's it's a protein protein that's naturally in most grains that we bake with, particularly wheat
is generally quite high in gluten.
There are some that are like low in gluten and some very few grains that we bake with that are gluten free,
including buckwheat.
For anybody that's ever confused by that buckwheat isn't a wheat.
It is actually anyway, I have so many things to say about gluten now that I have family members
that are allergic and a severe allergy, like can't can't even like can't eat anything that comes out
of my household, even if it is not even if I bake something that doesn't have gluten in it,
like any level of contamination is dangerous.
So so then we added in the extra bonus point for if you bake something gluten free, you get an extra
bonus point because it's a lot harder because that gluten is actually what gives structure
to everything every baked good basically.
So it's a lot harder to do gluten free baking.
So that was a whole lot of I'm sorry you get me started on this and I just have a whole lot to say.
I don't think this if people are hanging out here wanting to hear a stockpile group break off,
that is an excellent story.
Yeah, so very excited for this year.
We'll see what happens.
So we had a funny thing.
Okay, last last two family anecdotes around bake off on our draft last year.
I won't say any spoilers, but I will say there was
there was a so we actually formed a leftovers team because we we used to draft.
We'd watch the first episode and then draft, which left us we had five teams and they start
with 12 bakers.
So that left so one person leaves during the first episode that left us drafting 10
out of the remaining 11 and one person would just go undrafted.
Well, the only thing I'll say is last year in the first episode they didn't end up
sending anybody home.
So we had a full leftovers team with the two undrafted people and in a twist of fate last year
the leftovers actually won our whole family.
Draft so we all failed.
Stephen and Maria aren't actually the winners every year if we count the leftovers.
Yeah, we thought that I love the dedication though to the tracking that you tracked the
undrafted people.
Yeah, I am not I mean I am not the only person that likes accurate record keeping.
It turns out that it's a family trait.
It's a family trait.
We've got mathematicians, we've got lawyers, there's a lot of structured thinking happening.
So yeah, that was I'll stop talking about that but I'm looking forward to baking off
starting again and that extra motivation to try things that I don't actually even think I want
to bake but end up being a really cool learning experience and often like something fun and tasty.
And it's definitely a great show that is fun for the whole family like my husband and I watch it
together I know you watch it with your your husband and daughter like.
Absolutely, yeah it's super fun, super friendly and just much like ourselves fun and friendly.
Yeah, it's just so positive and if you enjoy baking or I mean you know your your husband
and my husband aren't I would not put them in the category of enjoy baking like you don't actually
even have to enjoy baking you know enjoy fun positive competition.
Yeah, do you have a favorite like do you have a favorite anything like a recipe or an episode or a
person like any favorite to share? Well, person is hard without going into spoilers though I will say
I did love that there has been one computational biology postdoc on the Great British Bake Off
I thought was great. Yes, representing those of us women in computational biology
but probably my favorite recipe is there is a smoked salmon soda bread from the COVID season
so it would have come out about 2021 so it's probably season 11 give or take that is so delicious
and so good and we still make it at home. Yes, absolutely I can second that I've made that one too
yeah it's uh we can jot these in our show notes or means smoked salmon and chive soda bread.
Yes, absolutely fabulous. That's a great one I think I you know a favorite of mine
surprisingly I think this is the one that stands out in my head the most these Devonshire splits
you know just beautiful like not actually that hard I mean they look stunning and
you know my finish work is never the strongest part of my baking we'll just leave it at that
but even you know even mine like came out looking much like this photo so I would you know
I would encourage this was a fun one and I love strawberries and like strawberries and whipped
cream on like a fluffy white you know sweet white bread like not not too hard to have experienced
baking bread this is this is one and I think even you know the this one the soda bread like
one of the easier soda bread is one of the easiest breads to bake so you don't even need
much experience baking bread I think it was the first thing my husband ever baked was made this
after I made it once so yeah yeah so this like even if you're not much of a baker yourself
recommend these couple of recipes so yeah I think I might need to buy some strawberries on my way home
yes I mean Wynn doesn't want me to buy like it's Friday afternoon what am I going to do I'm going
to buy strawberries on the way home yeah well enjoy your draft enjoy the great British Bake Off
hopefully you at home also enjoy the great British Bake Off thanks babe you too and um yeah all all
you fellow nerds out there let us know if you too love GBBO and what's your favorite recipe
yes and share recipes um because then we'll go bake them yeah awesome bye