Hey Beth!
Erin!
Is it time?
Is it time for another episode?
It is time!
We're here to talk about science!
That's my theme song of the day apparently.
I like your theme song.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, I wanted to talk about the Cell Painting Gallery today, also known as CPG, for those
who like acronyms or get tired of repeating themselves over and over and over again.
And yeah, so that's what I'd love to talk about today, you game?
Yeah, absolutely.
I love the Cell Painting Gallery and I want more people to love it too.
Yay!
So let's talk about it.
What is the Cell Painting Gallery?
So the Cell Painting Gallery is a really large data repository that we, the imaging platforms
as is co-maintained between our lab and the Carpenter's Thing Lab in the imaging platform
at Broad, and what it is is a whole lot of data, talking 700 terabytes-ish at the moment.
That's a lot of data.
A lot of data and growing.
That is all Cell Painting Assay or very close derivatives of that assay.
So I think, I don't think we've ever actually recorded an episode about the Cell Painting
Assay, which is kind of funny because it's kind of our area of expertise.
So I think we should probably do that real soon.
Yeah.
But, but the Cell Painting Gallery is a public data repository of high content microscopy
images of cells treated with compounds or genetic perturbations and with many organelles
or intracellular compartments labeled with vital dyes.
That's sort of the run-on sentence that explains the big picture of what's in the Cell Painting
Gallery.
So this is our landing page, which is a GitHub repo where most everything is here in our
docs.
I'm going to go through, I'll skim through our docs more importantly, but here on this
landing page, so this is, we use github.com/broadinstitute/cellpainting-gallery.
And the reason I'm starting here is to show you this is the list of available data sets.
So we have, we have this, you know, forward-facing list of data sets.
These are all fully complete published data sets.
So we list the identifier that we have given them to be able to find them in the gallery,
a brief description, publication in which these were described.
We also often have other GitHub repositories that have more information about these, this
data, particularly sort of the numerical data that supports the images.
So it could be links to, you know, links to GitHub repos where we show like the exact
code that was used for making profiles or, you know, the handling of the numbers we've
extracted from the images.
Or it can link to things more generally, like here, this explains comprehensive information
about a subset of these data sets, tools that you might use to interact with them, that
sort of thing.
So, so, you know, we link out to as much supporting information as we can.
It seems very thoroughly documented.
It is, because that's kind of my jam, yo.
Anyone that's listened to more than one episode has probably heard me say how much I love
documentation, and that's, that's my doing here.
Heavily documented, because that's what I love to do.
Yeah, give a girl right access to a repo, and next thing you know, documents just keep
appearing.
So we also give you an estimate of the size of both the image size as well as numerical
data.
So all of the images in here have been run through CellProfiler and had quantitative
measurements extracted on a single cell basis from all of these.
So that's what would be in the numerical data.
But important to know sort of what is the size of what you're handling, because some
of these data sets are larger than others.
For example, if it's like, hey, this looks cute.
It's, you know, it's a pilot episode, pilot episode, pilot data set.
So maybe I'll just download that to like get my hands wet playing around with some images.
But, you know, before warned that that's 6.1 terabytes of images in this pilot.
So maybe that's not actually, maybe you want to start it a little before you try to download
it to your desktop to poke around with the images.
So again, everything in the gallery is at scale.
And so that is a thing to keep in mind.
Also, this goes way back.
We curated in data that has been published like since the inception of the cell painting
assay, which is many years ago now.
And so other data sets have been in other public repositories at other points and
therefore given other identifiers.
So you may recognize data sets from the BBC, the Broad Bioimage Benchmark Collection.
You may recognize it from the IDR, which we have another Ask Erin Dear Beth episode
about the ID.
One of our first episodes.
Yeah.
And how much we love it.
So we have some, you know, we do have data in IDR as well.
So that's something to bear in mind.
But if you look, we actually have quite a collection of data.
These are all complete and published data sets that are available in the gallery.
There is also a ton of unpublished data that we are currently either collating in from
other sources, contributors are sending us data, or we are in the middle of generating
and analyzing them ourselves.
And as soon as we feel like they are complete, they will be moved here.
But if you want so you can poke around the gallery, everything in the gallery is fully
publicly available.
But if you want a complete, described data set, start with an identifier that here we
list on the main page.
So that's already a lot of data.
So there's a lot of data.
Yeah.
There's there's no shortage of data here.
So our docs, right?
Like Cell Painting Gallery has lots of documentation because that's my jam, yo.
And so we have a link to the docs, like here on the webpage.
Also, you can get straight there, broadinstitute.github.io/cellpainting-gallery.
And that will take you to our documentation about it, where it describes what's in the
gallery and how do you find stuff in gallery and how do how do you access it?
So there's a few that like, without reading you all of the docs, because if you're
really interested, you can go read them yourselves.
There's a couple of things I want to point out.
So first of all, fully publicly available, all for free.
It is hosted by AWS as part of their Registry of Open Data Program.
So thank you to AWS for hosting this data for us.
Thank you so much.
Access does not require an AWS account.
So you can access and download all of this without making an AWS account.
It is all free and publicly available, regardless.
You certainly can have an AWS account and you can use it, you know, use it to access
this data, use it to run compute on this data.
But you can, you don't need it and you can, you can do what you want with this data.
It is fully publicly available.
You can download it to your own server and do whatever you want.
So that's an important thing.
We have super stereotyped structure.
And this is probably the driest of the docs in here.
But if you are trying to find something, this is really helpful to look for because
it tells you exactly where to find it.
So if I know I'm looking for, you know, that CPG 000, that pilot, jump pilot,
and I want to find the images, right?
This explains exactly where I would find those images and what, like, based on their paths.
So, so if you're looking for something specific, this can be helpful.
And we talk about CellProfiler features.
And the, this is sort of information specific to the Cell Painting Assay and what we used
in the Cell Painting Assay to extract data.
So more on that in a different episode.
But we also here have information about how you can browse through the Cell Painting Gallery
and how you can download data from the Cell Painting Gallery.
And so I just want to show you, like, quilt is one example of an easy way to browse through
the gallery.
And so if I'm here looking in the Cell Painting Gallery here in this root folder, I see all
of, you know, all of the prefixes that have been added.
Again, not all of them are complete.
But I've been saying, like, OK, this is that first one I was interested in.
Let's go into the images folder.
And you can see, oh, look, there were six different batches in which data was collected.
Let's look at the images from this first batch.
And you can click through.
This is a plate of images as it came off of the microscope.
And anything is I can click on any of these.
And this is perhaps not optimized for scientific image viewing fully.
So can't see this image super well.
But if we also go into sort of the workspace, there is there is quantitative numerical data
that corresponds to all of these that one can see.
So if I want to look at, OK, let's look at the measurements made in some of these, I can
actually click on a CSV and have it previewed here for me.
And there's some some tools about actually viewing and doing some simple data viewing
and plotting within Quilt as well.
But really handy way, you know, intuitively to, like, click through and browse through
where data is without having to worry about understanding, fully understanding the either
object storage, which is how data is stored in S3 buckets, which is a whole, you know,
if you're used to working just like on a server or on your laptop, thinking about data in the
cloud as objects and bucket storage can be sort of a new intimidating thing.
So it's just a nice way to sort of browse through browse through and look for things.
That seems super helpful.
Yeah.
And again, here we, you know, we explain a few different ways.
Here's some examples of plots you can make, like in the browser in Quilt.
And sort of if you are more of a computational user, how to work with AWS command line interface
or this is a Python SDK for the AWS.
So instead of using the CLI, you can use Python and we give some examples there because most
of what we do is in Python in our lab.
So along with browsing, this is information about the actual download.
So if you want to download the files, this is information about how to do it.
And then just a couple of examples.
And here we welcome contributions.
If you have worked with the gallery and you, you know, have things to suggest here, we
have curated some workflows that work directly off of the Cell Painting Gallery.
So you can use, you can download the data if you want.
You don't have to download it.
And we provide some examples of different, this is like three different tools that people
have written that correspond, you know, were parts of different publications that are actually
showing examples of reading data directly off of the gallery and doing something with
that data.
You know, data at this scale can be handy for like machine learning and deep learning.
So a few of our data sets, more than a few, that's a decent number, are actually already
put into a format directly intended for interaction, you know, interaction with, you know, AI,
deep learning tools.
So we call, you know, call that out here.
Please cite the Cell Painting Gallery.
This helps us get funding so that we can get all the software and computational tools you
including the Cell Painting Gallery.
But this is, you know, citation information.
We do welcome contributions.
So if you are, if you are lab is generating cell painting data and you would like for it to be made
publicly available, let me know.
I would love to help you get the data in the gallery.
And we have here, you know, some examples of publications that are for the data in the gallery.
This is absolutely not comprehensive in any way.
But gives you some examples of if you want to, you know, read through them and maybe get a better,
you know, get a get an example glance at these and see like what what kinds of papers what kinds of
publications are describing these data sets.
This can can give you a good idea of that.
Yeah, I mean, that's sort of big picture of the gallery.
Like it's gigantic.
It's all cell painting data or very closely adjacent data sets.
And so what does that mean?
We have some, you know, for example, most most cell painting data is captured in an arrayed format where you
have a plate that has wells in it and each well has its own perturbation.
But we have the first published example of pooled cell painting where we're actually using sequencing by
synthesis on a per cell basis to distinguish what the what the perturbation is in an individual cell
within a pool.
So that's here.
We have ones that are, for example, like the site profiler is very similar to cell painting, but it is
tweaked a little bit specifically for like the acidic cells to better capture like metabolic
information. So it has Bo Dippy in it in many, you know, in the panel, which stains fat.
So helpful for specifically for looking at metabolism, you know, in fat metabolism and lipocytes.
We have some examples of data sets that are have paired perturbations.
So L 1000 is like mRNA profiling.
So we have data, you know, paired data sets that are not just cell painting, but they have like, you know, another
data type captured at the same time.
Yeah, we we have a lot of data.
It's really a lot of data.
And yeah, we welcome we welcome you to use it.
If you have any questions, let us know.
If you want to contribute, please let me know.
And yeah, I think that's the big picture of the Cell Painting Gallery.
Yeah.
Now available through the NSF's National AI Ready Resource Program.
That's true. We were just accepted to the NAI RR, another acronym, so many acronyms in science.
So we imagine so that was like just announced.
We imagine that over over time with inclusion in the in the pilot that there will be
a further expansion of people using this for AI research.
And so expect to see our curation of, you know, either MLDL ready data to grow or our ability to curate further
like MLDL workflows.
We imagine will be expanding as part of part of that inclusion in the pilot.
So we're pretty excited about that, too.
Yeah.
That sounds amazing.
What a great resource for people who want to look at cells.
Yes, absolutely.
And coming up in the not too distant future, we have when we get there, you know, when this is public,
we'll we'll definitely do another another episode on it.
But we're working hard in collaboration with another group right now to make browsing and poking around within the gallery across, like across all of the data there, even easier.
So we recognize that right now this is really most accessible to people with some level of computational comfort.
But we're working really hard on expanding that so that it's even more accessible to the average biologist who is not computationally terribly comfortable.
And like we hear you, we see you, you are our people too.
And stay tuned because we really hope hope that we have something exciting to show you in that realm as well soon.
Well, thank you for putting so much time and effort into making this so well documented and so usable and just like sharing all of these things with the community.
Yeah, it has been my pleasure.
Certainly when I agreed to help move a few files off of one S3 bucket to another at the very beginning of this project, I absolutely never pictured that it would be what it is now.
Because it is, it has been a pretty significant chunk of my time to make it what it is.
But I feel really proud of it and really excited for people to be able to have this resource, like believe really strongly in, you know, fair data, public data.
And I think the Cell Painting Gallery is, you know, our big contribution to the community in that regard.
So cool.
Awesome.
Have an awesome day.
Thanks, you too, hun.
Thanks for, thanks for talking CPG with me.
Always, anytime.