Hello Beth!
Hi, how are you?
Good to see you.
Always lovely to see you.
Always a lovely day when it's Ask Erin to your birthday.
Love it.
I agree completely.
I wanted to talk about Cell Painting again.
Because it's fabulous.
Why not?
It's fabulous and fun.
We talk about it a lot.
We'll drop, check out show notes.
We can link you to other episodes in which we have talked specifically about Cell Painting.
But this time I wanted to talk about a new meta resource that I put together that I thought
people would find helpful when wanting to dive in and become more expert at Cell Painting.
That seems super useful.
Yeah, so here we have the guide to Cell Painting for biologists.
So colorful.
Oh it is.
I was pretty excited when I figured out how to add in that rainbow gradient.
It's here at simonylab.github.io slash guide to Cell Painting.
And we'll have the link, show notes and all that.
But basically put this together for biologists, hence the title.
So people coming from a more wet lab biology less strictly computational math expert side,
coming from the biology side of things, wanting to know more about Cell Painting and how to
learn more about the different components, maybe how to run it themselves or how to dive
into some individual part.
So each question we've got here, it will say I ordered it in increasing complexity.
So if you find a question here and work your way, that's not chronological, work your way
numerically.
Down the page.
Down the page, down the page, that's a good way for it.
Work your way down the page because they get increasingly in the weeds as you go down.
So maybe if you're wanting a giant overview, just look at the first resource mentioned
at each of these.
And hey, actually, quite often the first resource is like, you know, go check out an Oscar and
Dear Beth episode.
Because for those regular watchers of our podcast, you know that these are kind of one of them
more casual resources that we produce, but hopefully kind of an easy way to get an overview
of things.
And then as you dive in, you then work your way into, again, more and more technical detail.
So it's arranged kind of by question that you might be asking as a biologist, even starting
with like, hey, what is Cell Painting?
I keep hearing this thing.
Tell me more about it.
I would like to know what this thing even is.
Then moving into what can Cell Painting do?
So here are some resources about the applications for cell biology that are common.
And what kind of questions, biological questions can be asked with this kind of data coming,
you know, and some examples of a couple reviews talking about linking you to a variety of cell
painting projects and the sort of diversity of biological questions that they're able
to answer best.
For those people who are wanting to perform the Cell Painting assay in a wet lab on their
own, the very first question we are often asked is, hey, can I change this at all?
Like how is that okay?
The answer is a giant yes.
And we haven't asked Erin Dearbeth on that.
We sure do.
So you know, start there.
But also a lot of details about yes, how you can do that, and different examples of how
other people have modified this assay to meet their own particular needs, whether that
is their own microscope setup versus their own sort of more tailored bit of biology that
they're wanting to dive into.
How to do image analysis on a batch of Cell Painting.
So this is definitely our, you know, biggest chunk of resources here.
This is what we do, what we are the world experts in to toot our own horn a little bit here.
What we do most often in our lab with Cell Painting data is really focused on the image
analysis.
And we have done image analysis on terabytes and terabytes and terabytes of...
We're probably closing in on a petabyte of Cell Painting data.
Yeah.
So we've touched a lot of Cell Painting images and have some pretty well tested ideas about
how to dive into doing image analysis and Cell Painting.
So here's a bunch of resources that can help one do the same thing.
Okay.
So image analysis is done.
And there's image features.
How do you turn those into profiles?
So part of the Cell Painting assay is taking, you know, finding individual cells and taking
hundreds to thousands of measurements on each cell.
How do you get from individual measurements of each cell into a single mathematical description,
a profile is what we call it, you know, you can call it a vector, like different ways
to describe it.
How do I take all of these single cell measurements and turn them into a description of each perturbation
that I have in my sample set, in my data?
Then once you have those, how do you find biology in them?
What do you do?
Because we're not doing all of this just for the love of crunching data.
Like we want to ask biological questions.
You don't just love making spreadsheets for the sake of having spreadsheets?
Well, I mean, okay, so sometimes I kind of do, but I understand that that's not most people's happy
place.
Also, I do want to point out that one does not need to do all of this on their own, right?
We've talked about the Cell Painting gallery a bunch through various episodes of Ask Erin,
Dear Beth, and it is a public repository that we maintain with, again, hundreds of terabytes
of Cell Painting data.
You don't have to do your own image analysis.
If you have a biological question, you could just jump into this point of, hey, I'm going to pull
profiles from a data set that somebody else has made, but I want to start exploring the biology
because for sure there is unexplored biology in all of these published data sets, you know,
while the researchers that initially made them and dove into them may have found something
interesting, there was guaranteed to be a whole lot more in each of these data sets that is
unexplored and also exciting and valuable to other researchers.
So here's how we just start exploring biology in these profiles.
And if you have a specific area of biology you're particularly interested in,
there's a lot further that you can go deep diving than this, but this is just a starting
point to help you kind of look for interesting tidbits that you might want to dive into.
Cell painting features.
So image analysis that we do with CellProfiler outputs, again, I said hundreds to thousands
of features and each of those has a name and this set of instructions here help you understand
what was actually, you know, this number I have in this spreadsheet, in this row and column,
like what does that number mean, what was it actually measuring based on the column name,
and this will help you understand that.
Where do we find published Cell Painting data? If I don't want to do all of the
lead up wet lab work, I'm just a biologist that's coming in and saying, hey, I have a question
and I want to see if these resources other people have created can help me answer my question.
This is where to start looking. And finally, what else can I do? Help, I'm still confused.
And having here the forum, we also mentioned the forum a lot, we even have an Ask Erin Dear
Beth episode about the best way to write a question on the forum. If you do want to
join our community and ask for help and, you know, a link to ways that you can contact us directly
to see if we can be helpful to you. So that's, I think there's one, I don't know if it needs to
be on this thing or not, but you can also contact us for the Ask Erin Dear Beth question
submission forum and submit questions there. Absolutely. I will go add that to our, to this
resource as soon as we're done recording, brilliant idea, Beth. Yeah, you can absolutely just ask us
and we'll answer it on the podcast. And oh my gosh, that would be fun. So yeah, that is the
overview of this resource, you know, this resource of resources. I really like that it's got things
for a whole bunch of different levels. It's got if you're some people are text people and some
people are video people, it's kind of got something for everybody here. It's really great.
Yeah, there's a lot of resources for how to get started doing Cell Painting.
There is, there is. And, you know, if it's not clear to watchers of the podcast by now,
like we love helping people, you know, we love, like, these are entirely things that we have been
involved in either, you know, our lab or collab, you know, close collaborator lab, you know, we,
we love teaching this stuff. We love helping other biologists learn biology and make discoveries. And
so, yeah, it's nice to have it. It was really fun putting this together, curating it in a way,
like we can take a step back and be like, Oh yeah, like, we've done a lot of really helpful stuff,
we should make it easier for people to find this really helpful stuff.
Yeah. Well, thank you for making it easy for people to get help.
My pleasure. Thank you for driving the creation of so many of these amazing resources.
Well, so lovely to see you talk to you.
You too dear. Sounds good. Bye.