Hello, my dear.
Oh, it's going pretty well.
I'm excited because we have questions from viewers.
Yay! Viewer questions! I love it!
I know. I always love when we have viewer questions.
In fact, we have two great viewer questions from Kavya from Helsinki.
So, for the next two of my episodes, we will be answering Kavi's question.
So Kavya, thank you for submitting these questions.
I love it! International, international image analysis questions
How fun.
Absolutely.
And they're really good questions too.
So I'm excited to talk about them.
So you too, please submit your really great questions
to Ask Arantier Path.
We'd love to feature them on the show.
So Kavya's first question.
I have been trying to implement QC
on my Cell Painting images
using features from Measure Image Quality.
I've been using PCA on the measured features.
I seem to have measured about 107.
And it seems like one of my cell types
is consistently different from the other
based on local focus score features.
What does this mean?
How do I interpret what some of these features mean?
Yes.
Yeah.
And that's a great question.
Because what do features mean in general
can be really difficult,
but it can be especially difficult
for some of these things like image quality.
And some of them get a little mathy.
Yeah.
So when in doubt,
I always start with going to the CellProfiler manual.
And this is the same exact information
that's in the CellProfiler module help.
So if you pull up the CellProfiler module help,
you will find all the same exact text
that's actually built from the same exact thing.
So there's a few different kinds of quality measurements
that CellProfiler makes in Measure Image Quality.
I'm going to start with some of the easier ones
to talk about,
which are not the blur ones that were in the original question,
but just because it's important to sort of mention them.
The intensity metrics can tell you again,
like how much intensity is going on.
And generally speaking,
that's not going to be a problem,
but these are great metrics for seeing
if some of your images are really different from the others.
So maybe they have a different maximum or a different minimum,
or maybe there's some accident of metadata going on
and they're scaled differently.
That would be potentially really dangerous.
So these aren't ones that are going to be good
for checking things like, you know, is my image blurry,
but they might indicate sort of overall problems
with maybe you've accidentally mixed in some eight-bit images
with your 16-bit images or something like that.
Threshold metrics.
So Threshold, CellProfiler can calculate the thresholds
as part of the Measure Image Quality module
for a bunch of the different thresholding methods that it uses.
And again, no individual threshold is wrong,
but it can help you see if there are patterns
where the thresholds are consistently different
between, you know, for a particular set of images,
where is the threshold being set?
Saturation metrics.
So what fraction of the images,
of the pixels in your image,
are either the maximal possible value
or the minimal possible value?
Because if you're at the ends of the spectrum,
you're no longer measuring quantitatively, right?
And so at that point, like,
there could be lower signal or higher signal
and you've lost the ability to detect it.
So no, trying to keep as little of your image as possible
above the camera maximum or below the camera minimum,
you know, helps make sure that, you know,
you're always in a quantitative range
when that's important.
Yeah, yeah.
It can also be the intensity metrics and or, you know,
saturation percent maximal,
found those really helpful for when there is some amount
of debris, like fluorescent debris in an image
that accidentally, you know, particularly fibrous sweater
dropping onto your sample someday,
will often be easily flagged.
The images that have, you know,
some chunk of very fluorescent,
something that's not supposed to be there,
will often be easily flagged by those metrics.
Great point.
And the last set of metrics are the blur metrics.
So blur can be kind of difficult to define.
So there's a few different mathematical approaches
that are here.
One of them is saying, what is the correlation
within particular areas?
So if I say, if I take a square of, you know, 50 pixels,
how likely is it that all the pixels are the same,
like are highly similar?
Because real biological objects
probably have a lot of variability if they're in focus.
If they're not in focus, they might have more sameness
because they're out of focus.
And so increased correlation can actually mean
that your image is blurry.
The focus score sort of operates on a similar principle.
It actually operates based on how much is the variance
in the image, the idea being if your image is blurry,
if the amount of like variance across the image
is very little, probably something is wrong.
It's not in focus because real biology sort of jitters.
And there's some great citations here for a bunch of these.
That one, they actually compared a whole bunch
of different methods across a whole bunch of,
oh, wrong paper.
No, no, something went wrong, of course.
They actually tried a whole bunch of different methods
and then they tested them across DIC images
and Brightfield and fluorescence and a whole bunch of things.
And actually we're able to say like across all kinds
of different things, like this particular method
often produces really good sort of measurement of blurriness.
So that is what CellProfiler refers to as the focus score.
The local focus score is just that and do it in tiles.
So this is the particular metric we were asked about.
So if I break the image into tiles, maybe parts of it
are in focus and parts of it are out of focus.
And so we can say what is that focus score
across the whole image and then get the focus score
for each and take the average.
There's also the power log log slope,
which I won't go too deep into the math for,
but basically it goes into the frequency space
of the textures in the image
and then takes the log of a couple of different metrics
and you say what is the slope of these particular lines
of measurements in frequency space?
If you think back to your Fourier optics,
high intensity information or high sort of noise information
is encoded in a different part of frequency space
than like big patterns.
And so the slope of this line actually helps indicate,
if the image is changing a lot,
if the textures change a lot
or if the textures are actually pretty smooth.
So the slope of that line changes.
So, self-prophetic provides you all of these.
And I wanna call up this paper in particular,
which is from the imaging platform
from a bit ago now from 2012,
that goes through some quality control workflows
and they actually did a really lovely job
doing some things with synthetic blurring
as well as taking some images
and then like physically,
figuring out the right focal plane
and then going 32 microns below and 32 microns above
to actually do a bunch of measurements to say,
well, like how far out of focus can we be
before we start losing our ability to detect
like our quantitative measurement and things like that
and measuring a bunch of these CellProfiler quality metrics
in these different conditions.
So this is a really nice paper.
And we in fact have,
and we'll put a link in the show notes,
a tutorial for looking at image quality
in CellProfiler that sort of uses some of these
measurement quality metrics.
But a couple of things that I wanna point out
are just that,
generally speaking, when you are doing these,
it's hard to draw hard cutoffs.
It's hard to say like one of the sort of
counter examples to that is you might be able
to draw a hard cutoff and say,
if more than 2% of my images is saturated,
I think there's too much saturation.
I can't get good quantification of intensity from here.
You know, I don't want this image anymore.
But for things like blurring and things like correlation,
especially channel to channel,
these things can be really different
and certainly experiment to experiment.
And they can be affected by things like confluency
because that will change the amount of intensity variation
in your image.
So usually we're not so much looking for a hard cutoff
as we're looking for the outliers.
So this is some CellProfiler analyst data
from the CellProfiler quality control tutorial.
And here we're looking at one of the image quality metrics,
which is correlation in the ER channel
at a scale of 20 pixels.
The higher this number is,
the more likely we think there might be a focal problem.
And so we can check a really low image.
For some reason, all of these look bad in linear scale.
That looks indeed like a perfectly fine image.
And then something with a really high value.
That indeed looks like a blurry image.
Yeah, totally.
One cannot deny that that image could be better.
But here's the next highest one.
And this doesn't strike me as terribly blurry.
There's a sort of out of focus-y guy
or like piece of debris there.
Let's check the other one.
But so this is where I say,
it can be really difficult to define exactly what's the cutoff
because this is the second highest well.
And this is fine, but this one is clearly not.
Yeah.
And to my point about channels,
so here, for example, is that power log slope
metric across two different channels,
the nuclear channel and the Golgi channel.
And the first thing I'll draw your attention to
is just the scales of these are different.
And even like this central blob here
is not like perfectly on a diagonal.
There is some scatter around here
that the power log log slope in one channel
versus the other might be different.
We can look at some of the outliers here.
And say, yep, this image sure looks terrible.
It's basically empty.
So clearly this is a bad image.
But some of these,
they might just be perfectly analyzable
but a little bit empty.
Or they might have a different metric
just because of a little piece of debris
that's off to the edge that wouldn't for me say,
I'm totally uninterested in this image.
I would just say, maybe I wanna mask
that part of the image out.
And it's hard, right?
Because we always want to try to figure out
how we can keep most of our data in.
Nobody takes data just so that they can throw it away.
That's not why we spend all of this time
sort of lovingly doing all these experiments
only to throw them away.
So I just wanna do one more here.
Oh, I didn't mean to move that.
Which is to show the one that Erin mentioned
which is percent maximal.
Cause that we can definitely use to find things like debris.
Yep, there we go.
That's a big old piece of debris.
That should not be there.
But these metrics can all help.
They can certainly be used to find things
but they can be really hard to sort of set hard limits on.
You can certainly decide to sort of say,
I'm gonna make a central clump based on some metrics
that I've checked in my data.
But for things like how consistent is the data
for different channels,
maybe really different for a nuclear channel
where we know it's not gonna be fully confluent
and a cell membrane channel
where we know if the cells are fully confluent,
there will be no background present in the image.
So we should be careful about setting hard cutoffs
and we should be careful about sort of
overly relying on these metrics
because they can be really hard to interpret.
But used carefully, they can help you identify
some of the real problems in your image.
And if you do the self-proferred quality control tutorial,
you can see how you can create classifiers
to throw them out if you do find hard limits
that work for you for your particular data set,
for your particular day.
Yeah, I think also what I found really interesting
is I think, okay, this is over time,
how we have used these QC metrics has changed.
I think some of that is changes in the field
and some of it is changes in the microscopy, right?
So we've found like the data sets that we are given now
are often have less debris and focus issues
than they used to, right?
Just autofocus on microscopes is better
than it was in 2012, right?
Things have changed technology-wise there.
So we are much less likely to get a giant set of images
in which there is a systematic focus issue,
meaning we are less reliant on actually pulling out
bad images from our data.
And I think we have also sort of moved then a lot further
from whole image rules and QC and filtering
into looking at the single cell level and saying,
okay, I've got some single cells like at the cellular level
where my measurements are crazy far off.
And maybe it's because, oh, this cell was totally out of focus
or this cell was underneath a giant piece of debris
and filtering that way.
But that requires a level of compute
that we, again, was totally different in access in 2012.
And so even what, not that I joined the lab in 2012,
but even when I joined the lab in 2019, right?
What we do now as common practice versus then
is still even shifted.
Yeah.
So all of that is a very long way to say,
I'm not sure exactly what the local focus score
being different for a particular phenotype means for you.
It could be something as different
as it's changing the confluence.
And so this metric, which says how consistent is,
you know, a particular region in its intensity
and then averaging that across the whole thing,
maybe there are more regions that are empty
or more regions that are full.
And therefore we're changing this value.
It could be something like that.
It could be that it's changing the height of your cell,
which is making it sort of be out of focus
like or seem more out of focus, even though it is in focus.
There's a lot of things that this could be,
but there's a lot of ways you can use this data.
It can just be a little hard to interpret.
Yeah.
I think that's everything I wanted to say
about quality control.
Yeah.
I think that's a great amount of information.
And, you know, we do have Ask Air and Dear Beth episode
on like interpreting CellProfiler features.
So there are certainly some that are very interpretable,
but the QC metrics, you know, as you mentioned,
are sometimes less so.
That doesn't mean they're not helpful.
And I think an interesting example of,
you know, you popped up the papers,
they had lots of deep math in them.
Like one does not need to understand the math behind these
to still know how to use them
or how not to use them that that's definitely,
but one can, you know, if you really want to,
the math is there.
And the CellProfiler manual tries to make it very clear
how to use them without necessarily needing
to sort of deeply study the equations.
Yes, absolutely.
Great.
Thank you so much for joining me on a viewer question.
We'll have another viewer question coming up
in an episode very soon.
Thanks for diving in with us
and thank you to our viewer for writing in a question.
To all our other viewers, please ask us questions.
Can we find them exciting?
Yeah.
Great.