Hey, Beth!
Hey, Erin!
How are you?
Peachie Keen, how about yourself?
What?
I love your scarf.
Oh, thank you.
I am mostly Peachie Keen.
I actually have a cold right now, so I'm doing that like old singers trick of keeping your neck nice and cozy.
Are you a singer then?
Well, in a past life, I've been many, many lives I have led up to this point, but yes.
I'm like something we should chat about in a future episode.
I think we might, because I happen to know that you might also have a past life as a singer yourself.
No.
So people might be wondering, and the question we get asked of like, how do we know so much about each other's past lives?
You seem to know each other awfully well for coworkers.
So we thought we might address that in this bonus episode of Ask Erin, Dear Beth.
Yeah, so we have to travel all the way back in time to get to know each other.
Yeah, so we have to travel all the way back in time to 2007.
Erin and I have known each other for a really long time, but Erin and I actually went to grad school together.
That is true.
And it's, although like, I don't know, time, time is not my strongest sense, the fact that 2007 was when we started grad school, like that doesn't actually seem possible.
And yet.
And Erin and I were in the same graduate program, which was really small and friendly, but also became very close friends and became very good.
I don't know how to use, say this without sort of just lots of curse words, but we would meet at Starbucks a lot for venting about exactly what we were not enjoying about our labs at the moment.
Yeah, there were, there were a lot of, you know, hey friend, Starbucks 10 minutes question mark, because what we were in, so we were in the same program at UC San Francisco, we did end up in different buildings.
So my building that I worked in was just across the street from the building that Beth worked in.
You know, same campus very close by but it turns out there was a Starbucks was like basically equidistant in between our two buildings so there was a lot of like OMG I'm really stressed like please come let me vent over coffee.
There was a lot of that.
I wonder the fact that now we sort of have this advice column together is based on this like, let me give you advice and then about our lab lives and how we both actually or at least I felt like I got a lot of value out of just being able to talk through some of my problems with somebody.
Absolutely. Absolutely. So, yeah, I mean I can't overstate how important it was for getting through hard times in personal life and hard times in science life.
So having a friend that, you know, can can say, hey, like walk up, walk away from your experiments right now I need a coffee buddy, and, you know, no questions either of us would quite happily drop what you were doing in the last walk away.
Yeah.
So in fact, that was such a strong bond that the even sort of post grad school life post COVID life. Erin was still one of the people in who I pitched to a lot of my life about how my life was so stressful.
But it turns out that that was actually how Erin and I started working together was basically me having a stress freak out.
Okay, so you and I tell the story slightly different way.
And the conclusion of it is, you know, so we were on a zoom with a group of friends from our grad school class that we have stayed in quite close contact with and it was just sort of like hey we haven't talked in a long time.
So let's let's catch up. And my version of this story is that I had just sold my so after grad school I left science, and I had just sold the business that I was running one of the businesses I was running and was sort of having a, I don't know what to do with myself, I am like clearly not happy
with being a business person. But I like, I don't know, I need something to do. I'm looking for the next thing I have some ideas but I want something to just like keep me busy during the day.
And I feel like I've got a thing to do, while I figure out what is the next, you know, what is the next version of my life, gonna look like and so Beth was in that same zoom saying, guys, I'm a little stressed out, I mean, that was my version of it,
I'm a little stressed out, because there were the postdocs and you're in your team had, you know, the way academia works completely unpredictably found jobs all at the same moment. And so Beth was left to doing more work than one person should be doing had new new people ready to ready to go but academia being what it is it was going to take a while for visas.
And the new people weren't slated to start for several months. And so I was like, hey, Beth, I've got an idea. I'm free, like I'm looking for a thing to do, you're looking for somebody to help you do the things that you're doing.
What, you know, maybe I could work for you for a few months.
Which I was immediately like, yes, I would love that, especially Erin and I, I had sort of forced her into using CellProfiler and graduate school, because I tried to force everybody I went to graduate school into using CellProfiler so she was like, you know, I have this and then you know, I can help you write some documentation
and Erin is the queen of documentation and I'm terrible at it for your new people to start so you can just dump your brain into my brain and I will write it all down which to me sounds like the best possible universe.
So I pitched it to my boss at the time Anne Carpenter. She was like, so wait a minute, you're telling me you want to hire your best friend, and she doesn't even live in the same city as we do.
And you think this is a good idea.
Yeah, no, this is going to be great.
Okay, I trust you if it's a tempting for a few months like if that's what you need, like do what you need to get things moving, because I was trying to do the jobs of four people simultaneously and I wasn't being four people.
We bet this amazing to be clear, she can do many people's jobs but for four was a little bit much.
Thank you.
And Erin joined as a three month temp six years ago.
And here I am.
I failed to be a temp.
Because as soon as you know, it worked really well and you know we'll say going into it we did have the conversation very clearly upfront of like okay, we both think this is going to be good but if it's not.
Our friendship is the priority. We will walk away.
Like hard feelings, because I have some experience of working with my husband in he runs a business and that was maybe not as good for our relationship to be working together and so I like I was very prepared to be like okay, you know, that might not work.
I mean, sometimes it doesn't work to work with a person that you love and care about because because so we had that conversation, but it turns out really well together. It was an amazing discovery.
Yeah, working with your best friend can either go incredibly well or incredibly badly and we are happily in the case where it has worked incredibly well.
Yes, absolutely.
You know, we have many complimentary approaches to things many, I mean lots of the same skill sets, which is nice because we speak very much the same language but then also, you know, lots of ways that we compliment each other.
You know, for example, I love documentation.
I bet it was not so.
Better at it than I used to be.
That is true. That is true. You are so much better.
I've had a good example to follow. I've had somebody who can teach me the value of good documentation.
Yeah, yeah, but like, that's my happy place. It's never going to be your happy place.
You can do it, but yeah, yeah. And so here we are six years later, working together.
Yeah, and I will insert one thing that the second that Erin started working here and was like, oh yeah, no, I totally get this. This is great.
Like we need to find her permanent project to stay because everyone who meets Erin immediately feels like their life would be improved by more.
Oh, that's very sweet.
I do feel very lucky. I mean, so I've been fully remote this whole time.
You know, the lab is clearly in the in Cambridge, the greater Boston area.
I've been informed that I can't just call it Boston. I'm a West coaster like always. So, yeah, so I live on an island outside of Seattle and one again an unusual setup to have somebody be fully remote in a position where nobody else is for six years.
But again, like we, we make it work. And it's been, it's been pretty delightful. Yeah.
And one of the great things about making this podcast is to spend more time together.
Yes, we do continually come up with excuses. You know, we have regular work things that we must do together but then also find excuses to have work things that we get to do together because it's a lot of fun.
So, should we end with maybe showing off a couple.
I was able to some. Oh, here we go. Like, this was the farthest back photo I could find of just me and Beth. So this is at a friend's wedding in 2010, which it turns out is a long time ago.
Make sure you made that outfit. Do I recall correctly? I know you made that.
Yeah, I did. I did make that outfit. Yeah, yeah, that was I did a lot of sewing at the time. So most of my own clothing.
And that was, yeah, that was one example. This is, this is my thesis defense.
It's a sad day.
Happy for you. Sad for me because you were leaving, but yeah, yeah.
2014 with Beth by my side, helping to celebrate another dress that I made.
You know, this is anti Beth in 2016 with my kiddo.
And yeah, another important and really special thing about getting to stay so close to to a friend for so long.
You know, my daughter who was not this size anymore loves, you know, even now at nine years old loves sneaking down when I'm in work meetings and seeing if anti Beth is on the screen during any zoom work meetings so that she can wave.
Because yeah, anti Beth love seeing her so.
Well, that is the brief history of the Erin and Beth behind ask Erin and Dear Beth.
Yeah, as brief as you and I ever tell stories with either of us ever tell.
No, neither of us are actually capable of short stories, but that's that's the shortest it gets I think.
Love seeing you as always Erin. You too, hon. We'll talk to you later.