Hey Beth! Erin! Hi! How's it going?
Peachy Keen!
You have fun things for us today?
Well, yeah, yeah. I think this fits under the definition of fun.
We'll see what you think.
I'm certain if you think it's fun, I'll think it's fun.
Yeah, certainly helpful.
So, you know, and much of the time helpful is fun.
It's certainly better than unhelpful.
Unhelpful, yeah.
So, what I was going to talk through quickly here is how to get object outlines into, that
have been made and exported by a CellProfiler pipeline, how you might get them back into
CellProfiler to be able to find those same objects.
So the reason, along with this just being sort of generally helpful, is that our, right
now our default analysis pipeline that we have used on many, many of our publicly available
cell painting data sets, particularly those within the cell painting gallery, we have,
so this is a folder looking at the files that were output for a single, single site, single
field of view, and we get the object measurements made on these objects that we've identified
within the image.
We identify cell, cytoplasm, nuclei, make measurements.
But we also...
I think we might learn more about the cell painting gallery in another episode.
I think that's a great idea.
We should do that.
Yeah.
So, the other thing that we output is these object outlines, and this is not something
that is unique to our data.
You too can output your objects as object outlines.
There are multiple ways that if you have identified an object in a CellProfiler pipeline that
you could save out those objects in image format to be able to then retrieve those objects
at a later date.
I believe...
So, a label matrix is probably one of the easier ones to take in, and in that you end
up with every object has its own intensity that corresponds to its object number.
But I believe we ended up...
Can you explain that a little bit more in detail?
I'm not sure I totally got that.
Yes.
Normally, I had an example readily available that would be super helpful.
How about...
Sorry.
What?
That's okay.
How about I import when...
Hold that thought, Beth.
I will show you in this pipeline as we go, let's import these objects, and then I can show
you the options for saving them out and what that looks like and how you might handle those.
We'll come back to it.
Okay.
Since you're making me think on the fly here.
I knew you can handle it.
I think so.
I think we'll get there.
These images, I believe we settled on outlines because these are much smaller in file size
than many other options for saving out images because they are zeros and ones, black and
white of just...
Here we go, where you see most of the image is black and then the objects are outlined
here in little white outlines.
I have downloaded just a random example of the two corresponding cells and nuclei images
and I put them in a pipeline here.
So I have cell outlines and nuclei outlines.
It's really easy.
This is the whole pipeline for getting them in because we have a CellProfiler plugin.
We already have another Ask Erin Dear Beth episode about CellProfiler plugins.
So go check that out for more information about CellProfiler plugins, how to use them,
how to find them.
The show notes.
We'll add it to the show notes.
The link, yeah.
So go check that out if you're not familiar with CellProfiler plugins system.
But this is a plugin that is available in our repo and the plugin is called convert outlines
to objects.
And so quite handily what it does is converts outlines to objects.
Go figure.
So here in test mode, I can show you what this does here.
All I did was say this nuclei outlines image.
I want you to input that and name the output object nuclei.
So it defaults to say the typical diameter of objects goes from zero to infinity, which
that's quite a range for big nucleus.
And what we can see is that it has done a mostly brilliant job.
But what we have, so what we have here in the colors are the nuclei that it figured
out from these object outlines.
So what we would hope for is that these nuclei objects would be on a black background because
we don't want this giant green infinite sized or the rest of the image sized object.
So what we can easily do is say, okay, here's the biggest nucleus that I'm seeing on this
image.
It has a length of about 96.
And so I'm going to triple that and say my typical object diameter goes from zero to
300 and bam, there we go.
Done.
How many nuclei?
Nuclei, nuclei, anything are generally the easiest object to the identification tasks
for compartments within a cell because they're generally pretty round and generally fairly
separated because there's usually the rest of the cell keeping them from bumping up next
to each other when cells are next to each other.
So this is a pretty easy task, but really lovely that it just kind of works.
So then we can do the next step of the cells.
And I already added in here typical diameter of cell objects because it was doing the same
thing as the nuclei initially in identifying the whole background.
And you can see there are probably some regions that get identified as, okay, so if I go back
to zero, there's probably some regions here that are...
No, actually, that did pretty good.
One could expect, right, if we zoomed in here, it might think this is an object, this little
object here, it might think this is an object here, but it actually did a great job of just
figuring that out.
But playing around with these...
I pressed O instead of zero.
I was about to...
Yeah.
I pressed O instead of zero.
There we go.
I shouldn't allow you to put the letter O in there.
Somebody fix that.
Maybe I'll go file a bug report.
And there we go.
This is what I was expecting to show here.
So it thinks this is all these tiny regions.
It thinks this is a cell.
It thinks these little gaps are cells.
These tiny little gaps are cells.
These tiny little pixels, you know, blank pixels in between, and that we don't want.
So if you input a number instead of a letter to be fixed, live demos, right?
That is why I had set the typical object diameter of minimum of 20, and then it nicely sees
the number.
And then I had set the number.
And then I had set the typical object diameter of minimum of 20, and then it nicely sees
that, oh, these tiny little bits in between are not actually cells and doesn't identify
them.
One thing that sort of an extra thing that we could do now...
According to these nuclei and cells, where did you go?
You closed it.
I closed it.
Yeah.
I sort of unfortunately default too much to just automatically cleaning up after myself,
and then I clean up probably more than I should.
I think cleaning up is bad.
Yeah.
So if we look at this, I can still see at a glance regions like I doubt that's a cell.
I bet that is blank space that is not supposed to be there.
But there are a couple different things that we could do now to clean this up further.
So if we...
One option is in our output measurements, this would be something downstream.
So if I wanted to take these objects that I found and use them to do some additional
measurements, one thing that could happen is if we look at our cells, there are columns
that have area-shaped bounding boxes or information about the center, the x, y values of the center
of the objects.
And so if I took these cells as we identified here and made a bunch of measurements on them,
if I wanted to be sure that they matched perfectly with existing measurements I had made here
that I was importing them, I could use the bounding boxes or the cell centers to perfectly
match and filter them out on my downstream data.
Another option, and this is another plugin that we have, there's an enforce objects one-to-one.
And so this is another option if you want to get all experimental because plugins are deemed
experimental and not guaranteed to work.
I mean, we hope they do.
So if they don't work for you, file a bug report and we'll get there to fixing them.
But plugins are our experimental area.
So this is something new, fairly new that we've been working on developing.
And you can say, okay, these nuclei are my pre-primary objects.
These cells are my pre-secondary objects.
And what we can do then is run this module and we should see...
There we go.
What we see here in this current output view is that the nuclei and the cells have been forced to have a one-to-one
relationship so that we then, in this way, are getting rid of any of the secondary objects that don't nicely have
their own nucleus.
And so you can see this number of pre-primary objects.
So the input nuclei, there were 66 objects.
The secondary objects, we actually had 86 cells found in our image, but the number of enforced objects that came out is
66 so that managed to filter out 20 of the...
Right, so if we zoom in here, this little bit was not supposed to be a cell.
And you can see in our output objects here, it has been filtered out.
It is no longer identified as a cell.
So that is a handy way to force these to play nicely, to quickly and easily clean up these secondary objects
if you have this parent-child relationship, particularly, again, nuclei and cells where nuclei are really easy
to identify those objects coming in.
And cells can be a bit trickier because of the way the objects are touching and might have tiny gaps in between them.
That's a very smart way to do that.
I really like that idea.
Yeah, it's pretty fun.
This is a fairly new module to CellProfiler plugins that have been having quite a bit of fun with.
Yeah, so then one other thing I said full circle, and I said I would show you now.
If we add another module of...
Oh, okay.
So here, actually, we need to make...
Wait.
Yeah, we have to make...
Make our label matrix image.
And then...
So we need convert objects to image.
There we go.
Look at me just doing this on the fly.
No stress, I swear.
I'm not stressed.
You don't seem stressed.
Yeah.
So in this example, we can take our cells, or here we...
I don't know, our secondary objects with our nicely filtered ones.
We select an output image name here, cell image will work.
And then these are different ways that we can output those images to be able to save them.
So I can actually just show you really quickly what those look like.
So if we had this color map, if we wanted to output this as our cell image,
it looks much like the module, our module display,
that we can use to save out.
And one could change the color map.
So there's probably...
Oh, let's see a brief...
The pink-green is always my favorite, but I don't remember the exact...
I won't...
I knew it.
I figured it out.
Look at that.
So one could change the color map and make it look like they want...
This is maybe not the most actually helpful or informative color map,
but it is fun because it is pink and green.
The jet haters in the audience will appreciate you changing away from jet.
Yes.
Other options here, this binary.
This is just going to output as zeros and ones,
leaving these single pixel gaps in between our objects.
So this is another way that this could be output.
If we go to grayscale, so this is what is often referred to as a label matrix.
So if we start...
So we have...
So right down here where I'm currently moving my mouse,
when we hover, that is the pixel intensity where it shows up.
So in the background, we have a value of zero,
but as we hover over different cell objects...
5, 7, 5, 8, wait.
I just got confused.
What are the values scaled by, Beth?
So in grayscales, it's going to be zero to 55.
So grayscale is great for when you have up to 255 images,
but cell profiles, I assume you want as a literal grayscale,
which in cell profiles world is zero to one.
If you want to make it the actual integer numbers,
so say all the pixels of object one are labeled one,
you're going to need the last option.
Yes.
So the increments here are from zero to 255,
scaled zero to one, whatever those...
So that's why we're getting non...
sort of what seems like an odd number of this has a value of 0.618, right?
So...
Although it seems like maybe the...
So here it might just be evenly scaled.
So I would have to check, but I think it might just be evenly scaled,
which I mean, it's going to be a great picture,
but not actually helpful for making a label matrix.
Importing objects, right.
So we have...
So the number of cells are scaled across the gray,
the gray tones is zero to 255, that makes sense.
So again, this would be one that might be helpful for visualizations,
but not as helpful for actually data exportable images.
So the data...
Exportable data that you can then import easily.
So the final here is this gives us...
So CellProfiler, almost all the pipelines default to having everything scaled zero to one.
But here, this will output an image...
where it's still showing us intent...
Again, do-do-do...
Yep, here we go.
You have to tell it to make a change and then tell it to apply that change.
Okay, no longer confused.
So here, this is no longer using the zero to one scale
that CellProfiler typically enforces for gray scale anything,
for most of what it does.
But here, this would be what we would actually consider a label matrix,
where each cell has its own integer value.
So this is cell number 20, because when I hover on it, it has an intensity of 20.
This is cell number 42, because when I hover on it, it has an intensity of 42.
So this is the label matrix that I was mentioning in the beginning,
and Beth was forcing me to show you because that's helpful and a good suggestion.
And so one could make this image here as my cell image or my label matrix,
and then have a save images module where I am saving my label matrix.
The one thing that you want to pay close attention to here,
is that depending on your number of objects that you may need,
if there are many, many objects, you may need something larger than 8-bit.
So something to bear in mind, because you may max out if you have lots of objects in your image.
But that would not be a problem for this 65 cells that we have in this image.
But for example, if you were identifying small foci in a large image,
and you have lots of them, that would be something where you would want to double check
that your actual image export, your saving of your image is in the format that will retain all of your data.
And this U at 16 I think is also going to be better for making sure that object 3 always has the values of 3,
no matter how many objects originally started.
I didn't realize that about grayscale, so you taught me something new about CellProfilerprofiler today.
That's awesome. I taught me something new. We stumbled into something new!
Yeah, well, that's what I had to show about getting those objects into a pipeline and doing something with them.
That seems great, because then you can make sure that when somebody tries to compare how they measured something
and how you measured something, that we're all measuring the same thing, and that's really important.
Yes, absolutely. And a really handy thing, I think, you know, hopefully pipelines themselves don't get lost,
because if you have the same CellProfiler pipeline, we'll always output, we'll always identify the same cells in the same order.
So if you run the exact same pipeline on the exact same images, you will get out the exact same cell objects.
But sometimes pipelines themselves get lost to history, and so if you have the object saved out,
that is a really nice way to make sure that you can still, you know, still have the existing data as a starting point
and build upon it in whatever you're working on, even if the original pipeline is gone.
Awesome. Well, thank you so much. That was so informative.
My pleasure.
Have an awesome day.
Thanks, you too, hun. Bye.