Hey Beth!
Erin, it's so good to see you!
You too!
How are things?
Lovely!
We've got some sunshine here right now, which is always nice.
Sunny and maybe a bit too sunshiny here today.
What I wanted to talk to you about today is a tool called ilastik, and more in general
the idea of pixel classification.
What that is, why that is, why it might be helpful.
Because ilastik is one of our favorite tools, and we end up using it a lot, especially for
projects that are a little bit trickier.
So I wanted to sort of let everybody know that this resource exists.
Awesome.
I love new tools.
All right.
Let me go ahead and share my screen.
And I think something worth double pointing out that despite, as image analysts, despite
being the team who maintains CellProfiler, we use lots of different tools.
And any image analyst, you may have your favorite tool.
I think we've shown in lots of episodes that we often, the very first thing we do is look
at images in Fiji, even before moving into a CellProfiler pipeline.
And just something to point out that you may be an expert in a given tool, but that doesn't
mean it's the best.
And there's lots of awesome tools out there, and ilastik is one that we love and use all
the time in our lab as well.
Yeah.
CellProfiler might even be our favorite multi-tool, but sometimes you need just a really darn
good screwdriver.
Sometimes you need another tool that's better at what you need to do than the thing that
is your go-to standard.
And we love ilastik for things where doing segmentation can get a little bit complicated.
Absolutely.
So here's one example.
So these are some cells that were taken with phase contrast imaging, where we're using
just white light.
We're not doing any fluorescence.
And by eye, I can really confidently say, you know, this is the boundary of this cell.
This is the boundary of this cell, because our brains evolved over millions and billions
of years to do that.
A program like CellProfiler that's used to dealing with fluorescence images is going
to get really confused because it's going to say, like, hey, you told me to look for
bright things on dark backgrounds, and that's not this.
We may, in a future episode, talk more about how what are the ways that you could make an
image look more like this.
But one of the tools that makes it really easy to make these cells look bright on a dark
background is ilastik, and this idea of pixel classification.
Ooh.
So there's a lot of different things you can do with ilastik.
I'm just going to be, like, skimming the surface here.
But this is a set of things that we generally find really helpful.
Oh, no.
I think I can just drag it around rather than having to spend five minutes sort of exploring
my whole.
I can.
Thank you, ilastik.
So I've brought in a bunch of these different images.
And ilastik is going to ask us to pick some features.
This isn't going to mean anything or it's going to mean more once I actually start working
with ilastik.
So I'm going to go ahead and just select these and then come back to telling you what they
are and why.
I'm going to hold you to that.
Okay.
You do, please.
All right.
So here I'm given this idea of two labels.
Two labels doesn't mean that much to me.
Let's say I would rather call these background and cells.
Because there's two kinds of things in this image.
There's background in their cells.
Depending on how pedantic you want to be, there are more kinds.
There's little bits of shadow and things like that.
But there's two major kinds of things that I want to know.
I want to know is this part of the background or part of the cell?
And so the way I'm going to teach ilastik to do that is I'm going to drop my brush size
down to one.
And in a feature episode, we'll explain why it's important to drop your brush size down
to one.
But it's really important to drop your brush size down to one.
Just take my word for it.
It's not usually that we say, like, this is a rule and follow this rule and it, you know,
we'll explain why later, right?
Or not explain why, but this is a rule.
Like very rarely do we have moratorium or mandates.
There we go.
Very, very rarely do we have mandates without sufficient explanation because we love teaching
and training.
But this is just this is a mandate.
Just trust us or episode.
Keep an eye out for the next, you know, for a future episode where we explain why.
So I'm going to ask ilastik, what is the difference between background and cells?
And so I have to teach it.
What is it differently in background cells?
And so the way I'm going to do that is I'm going to annotate it.
I'm going to start literally by just annotating one pixel in each cell.
I'm now going to hit this magic live update button and magic is going to happen.
You ready?
Ready for magic?
I don't know.
Let's do it.
What?
So ilastik has turned all of the pixels of the background yellow and all of the things
that it thinks are cells, it's turned blue.
I'm going to add just a second one.
Okay, hold the phone Beth.
That was with literally two pixels.
Yeah.
Yep, it was.
Literally two pixels.
It already.
Yeah.
And if I turn on my segmentation, it's pretty good.
Wow.
What actually happened?
How does the magic work?
So if I turn off live update and go back to the feature selection mode, I told you I would explain.
Okay.
What ilastik said is, okay, you gave me two and then later a third pixel for each one
of the things that you told me to measure.
So little circles around that pixel, very small pixels, 0.3 pixel diameter, including
big pixels, 10 pixel circle diameter, measure things about the color of the pixels in that
area, measure things about the edges that are around that pixel, measure things that
about the texture of that part of the image, and then make a classifier.
So this is why we call pixel classification.
So if it says, hey, the texture here is really different than the texture in the background,
which by my eye, I'm pretty sure is true, then it will use something like the texture
to say, I can classify if this pixel and this pixel versus this pixel have different properties
and I can learn to split those things apart.
And in fact, it will actually suggest what are the most important features and I bet
they're going to come up as texture features, but we can kind of see.
So it's going to ask what the features it should use are.
And I'm just going to hit run feature selection and see what happens.
Live demo. So who knows, but.
So actually, it's about different smoothing things.
So there you go.
It wasn't exactly what I predicted, but how the image changes when you smooth it.
Interesting.
Yeah, I imagine has some relationship to texture.
But, you know, a different way of mathematically approaching that.
Yeah, I also have only given it a very small number of pixels to learn from,
possibly if I gave it more pixels.
I'm going to, for example, it said that this was, it thought was a cell.
Change that and put a background label there and now see if, oh, I have to turn out
my update for magic to happen.
Magic happened.
And so there's a couple of little holes in here.
I could spend more time, but with just a couple of pixels, literally four.
If I zoom out, you can see I've done a pretty good job on this image.
And if I switch to some of the other images in my data set.
Oh my gosh.
Those are looking pretty good too.
Four pixels, completely different images.
Like that's us.
I want to show you actually even a more fun example of so both of these image sets
are actually things that I found in the bird bio image benchmark collection,
or the BBBC.
So.
Go ahead and restart ilastik.
So here we can see why CellProfiler might not do a good job because it wants
things to be bright in the background dark.
And that's not what we have here.
Here, our background is dark, but what we have here are actually, these are
synthetically made cells, but they're cells of lots of different shapes and colors.
The nuclei are always blue, but I think that's a good idea.
But the authors here computationally made a bunch of cells with lots of different
colors so that they could test how well classification algorithms worked to
classify a cell as red, green or blue.
So I thought that was a cool data set.
And you can imagine that, especially if I care about the difference between the
nucleus and these cytoplasms, that it might not be super easy to tell cell
profiler maybe the difference between where what parts of the image are cell
and which parts are background, but maybe not the boundaries of individual cells
because there are lots of different colors.
So again, I'm going to make a pixel classification project.
And as always, we will put the links to our data sets in the show notes
because we love to share good data.
All right. So again, I'm going to turn on my feature selection.
And so the last time I had two classes, now I'm going to have three classes.
I'm still going to call this background.
I'm going to actually change the color also just because I don't
kind of actually don't want to see the background.
I'm going to display very much.
We're going to call this nuclei.
We're going to call this cell.
All right. So we still have our super small brush.
Going to do a pixel of background.
Let me zoom in a little.
Let's do a pixel of nuclei and let's do a pixel of cell.
And then let's watch the magic happen.
Show us the magic.
All right. What did we get?
So it definitely knows background.
And for some of the cells, it knows cells.
And for some of the cells, it's really not sure.
If I turn on ilastik's uncertainty view,
it's kind of, so here uncertainty is marked as teal.
It is pretty certain or more certain anyway in the cell that we marked as part of a cell.
It's really uncertain in the green cell because we haven't actually annotated it with anything green.
Yeah.
This is where our discussion about overfitting and stuff comes in,
which we're going to talk mostly about in another episode.
But let's see if I can get something to work.
So I'm going to break my rule.
I'm going to try to make my cell here.
I'm going to turn on the big brush and I'm going to give it lots of cell pixels that are red.
What happens to our segmentation guess now?
It actually did pretty well.
And I'm pretty sure the reason that it did pretty well is because we have texture features here
that are similar, I mean red and green.
I suspect that if we set this to only use intensity features and not some of the texture or smoothing
features, we actually wouldn't get such a good result.
What you're saying is it's probably actually just ignoring the color now when you've added
many of those other pixels and focusing on what is similar between the two.
Yeah, which we can check.
Yeah, so these are now definitely getting into some very texturing features.
It's kind of ignoring the colors.
If it had had a hard time learning this green, the more that I sort of annotated red,
the more green I would have had to add in order to get it to go well.
One way I still might be able to show you that is the nuclei I haven't annotated very much yet.
If I put, and it's not doing a very good job because it's now seen so many cell pixels,
it thinks most things are cells.
See if I drop just a couple more nuclei pixels.
So now I maybe have like five nuclei pixels.
What do I get?
All right, it didn't take very many this time.
And that's probably because this is a pretty easy task and the nuclei are a different texture.
So I wasn't able to get it to overfit this time because ilastik just has so many useful
features that it does such a good job that I'm not actually able to demonstrate overfitting.
But we will have another episode where we talk about the importance of being able to actually say
that the number of annotations that you make in each kind of phenotype that you're looking at
actually matter.
But I think we can.
Oh, sorry.
I just one thing I'm noticing is with this latest prediction, it looks like it's predicting
nuclei in the middle and then cells around it, but then sort of a layer of nuclei again.
Yeah, I noticed that too.
I suspect why is because it thinks that nuclei are things surrounded by cells.
So if we and so if we put a bunch of annotations in the background just far from the cell,
I'm not sure if that'll fix it.
We can figure that out.
So that didn't do much to fix it.
But I suspect if we put examples right there sort of close to the cell.
And that was just one more pixel.
But one pixel in the right place made that huge difference when a whole bunch of pixels
in a place it was already doing well actually change anything appreciably.
Yeah.
And that's a really great point.
So let me let me demonstrate that now even a little more, which is let me erase all those
pixels.
Let me turn on the uncertainty view.
Right now, the places that I put those pixels initially are pretty already darn certain.
So it doesn't matter if I sort of draw out here all day.
The things aren't going to change much because, you know, I've now made this uncertainty even
less, but I haven't actually fixed my segmentation.
Problem at all.
But if I go to where the uncertainty is high,
then I can fix my segmentation much more easily with many fewer pixels and fewer pixels is
always better as we'll talk about in a future episode.
Lovely.
But yeah, ilastik is really great.
You can see it's robust to all kinds of shenanigans that we can try to throw at it,
even when we're trying to throw at things.
But it's a great way to make your image into sort of the thing I care about is found specifically
even if the thing is not is all the same color or as many different colors,
both of which sub profiler struggles with.
And so those are there are many use cases for using ilastik.
Definitely check out their website.
We'll put it in the show notes, but those are some of our favorites.
Absolutely.
I think one thing too, and maybe this is for a future episode is that,
you know, often we are using multiple tools in a single analysis task.
So here ilastik has done a brilliant job of getting these objects for us.
And then we may take these objects and bring them into a CellProfiler pipeline
and make the measurements that we're interested in in a cell pro in a CellProfiler pipeline,
bringing in these objects.
And then even within the CellProfiler pipeline,
you can do the things that you're familiar with, perhaps familiar with already in cell
profiler about, you know, around object identification, we could fill the holes there
or smooth it out or, you know, add or subtract a bit of, you know,
some number of pixels to the edge of the objects.
So lots of lots of extra things.
And the holes are definitely there more in the green than they are in any other color,
because it knows the least about green.
Yeah, we moved a little bit.
And here we would have a lot of uncertainty just because it never saw a blue cell.
So the red cells definitely perform much better than the green and blue ones.
Yeah, absolutely.
So that'd be something you could either continue to improve your pixel classification here in
this pipeline, or if this was the best you had, bring it into another tool like CellProfiler to,
I mean, already one more pixel and it's so much better.
But, you know, you can bring those into CellProfiler to then do further work with.
Couldn't have summed it up better myself.
Sorry if I took the words wrong.
No, no, it was beautiful.
You put on air and I jumped ahead.
I just got excited.
Good image analysis is always exciting.
Of course.
All right, so good to see you.
See you next time.
All right, sounds good.
Bye.