Hey Beth, hello! So good to see you. You too. Thank you for joining me here on part three
of three in talking about working with collaborators. So if you have not yet watched one and two
do go back and do that because they think it'll be really helpful. But this one in particular,
we're going to be talking about working with difficult collaborators. So go watch the first
parts because they definitely set up what I'm going to be talking about here. But hopefully
this will be helpful for those of you who have a difficult collaborator, difficult situation,
give you some ideas about what to do. Yeah, it's hard because you want to like everybody that
you work with. But sometimes priorities are misaligned or communication didn't happen
in the lovely ways that you've laid out before and you're just ending up in a situation that
isn't good. And while we try to avoid ending up there, sometimes that's where you are.
Yeah, yeah. So go back and watch the first two episodes because they talk about
setting expectations and then sharing some tools for setting expectations that will hopefully help
you avoid difficult collaborations. But sometimes that still happens, even with best intentions,
sometimes situations end up being difficult. So now I'm going to talk about that for a minute.
So I guess first I just wanted to say, you know, like a little bit of brainstorming on like what
makes a difficult collaboration because this may look different for different people.
You're, you know, my view of like what is difficult, maybe different than somebody
else's view. I think the things I'm going to say apply to any form of difficult, right?
But, but, you know, I guess I just want to say here that like your version of what is difficult
may be different. And therefore the help that you need in figuring out this difficult relationship
may be different and that's okay. And sometimes somebody is not, it is a difficult collaboration
without somebody being a difficult collaborator. Absolutely. Like sometimes, like somebody is
a perfectly loving collaborator for somebody else, but not for you. Yes. Not saying that if you find
it difficult to work with somebody, they're a bad person. Absolutely. Absolutely. And they're
might not work well with you. Yes. Totally. And maybe even, you know, with you under the
certain circumstances, like we have certainly encountered times where we have loved working
with a collaborator and it has been fine. And then something about the circumstances changed.
Like it turns out they're great when we have no time limit, like then things go really well. But
when there is a hard deadline, things get too stressful and unearths some, you know,
difficult interactions. And so even the circumstances can change and make a collaboration
difficult in one scenario when it is not in another. Yeah. So I just wanted to, I mean,
unfortunately, difficult collaborations, difficult collaborators, it happens. And
as I said, go watch the first two episodes because there are, hopefully, there are a lot of ways to
avoid these situations. But when you end up in a difficult situation, I have just a couple tools
here to help. So the first one being find your champion or your protector. This can be very
different depending on the setting that you are in. You know, when I initially put, you know,
when I initially gave a presentation like this to our lab, there was, you know, a picture,
a picture of Beth front and center and then, you know, and then me and Nodar as team leads
within the lab, you know, so we are, you know, we want to be the champions and protectors of people
that are working in our lab in our team. And so if a postdoc or RA in our team is having a hard
time having a difficult interaction, difficult collaboration, you know, we want to be the person
to be able to step in and help resolve the situation, help ease the situation. We want to do what we
can, what is within our power to make that not good go away. And so that may be your PI. That's
great or boss. That's great. You may not have that relationship with your PI or boss. You may need
to look elsewhere. If you are in graduate school, that could be staff in your graduate program,
that could be your thesis committee. That could be, you know, if you were in academia, an ombuds person,
you know, or a union, a department head, like any of any of these things, it could be
an external mentor, somebody that is not directly in a, you know, a reporting structure
or hierarchy within your organization. It could be somebody else entirely. And in fact, we encourage
people in our lab to build relationships with mentors that are totally outside of our immediate
structure. Because they can, you know, even for purely good reasons, they can provide networking
opportunities that are totally separate maybe from what we can provide. They can provide experience
and mentorship coming from a very different perspective than we can provide given that the
constraints that we're in. So having an external mentor can be very helpful. So hopefully, if you
were in a difficult situation dealing with a difficult collaborator, you have somebody
that you can turn to and ask for advice or ask for them to step in, you know, depending on what
the situation is. But the big thing I want to point out with this is that like you are not alone,
you should not be alone. And somebody should be able to help you. And if it's not, you know, if
you don't have a boss as amazing as Beth, then, you know, I'm sorry, that may not be it. It may not
be, again, the person you directly report to and that's a bummer, because I wish for everyone
that they directly reported to somebody who they felt like they always had their back.
But even if you don't, you find somebody that can help you in this situation.
And they don't necessarily have to intervene, but just someone to advise you and help you and
make you feel heard. Yes, yes, absolutely. That sometimes, sometimes even having somebody say
to you, like outside, like in life, big picture statement here, having somebody say to you like
yeah, I hear you, that stinks. I'm sorry, you're in that situation. That is not good. I hear you
and I understand why that feels not good. Sometimes that makes a huge difference. Just
hearing like you are not alone. Like, I am here for you. I care about you. I see that this is crummy.
I don't want that for you. Totally.
No. This is a really important word and it's a really hard word. And sometimes the solution
to a difficult collaboration is saying no. And what that can look like can be different. The
situation may need like, there are both very gentle nose and very assertive nose. And
both what comes naturally to you as a person and what is suited for the situation can be different.
So, you know, a gentle no, like, I'm sorry, I can't do that. You know, I apologize for this.
Thank you for your, you know, thank you for your suggestion. But like, unfortunately,
oh, here's an alternative. Right. Like, gently saying, no, but, right. Like,
that maybe something that, you know, you can again, like going to your mentor or getting some
coaching on, okay, how do I politely and gently tell this person no, like, I don't know, I can't
do what they were asking for. No, I don't think it's reasonable. No, it's not within the scope of
what I can and should do. Or, you know, no, you can't treat me that way. That's not kind.
Like, no, I, you know, no, stop that. Maybe you need some coaching about how to say that gently
to a person so that the relationship and conversation remains friendly and professional.
On the other hand, some people also need coaching on how to be assertive about it.
Like, how to say directly, no, period, no is a full sentence. I can't do that. No, that is not my
priority. No, that is not what we talked about in the beginning. I need to follow the initial set of
expectations that we set, period. And if that doesn't come naturally or comfortably to you,
again, if you have a champion, hopefully that's something that they can help you with, either
coaching you, practicing with you, or even just giving you the boost of support of actually,
that's okay to do. If you're not naturally assertive enough in these situations, and somebody is pushing
you and pushing you in a way that is not comfortable, it is okay to be direct in response.
Having them read a draft of an email and help you make it more assertive?
Yeah, absolutely. So in a difficult, in a difficult collaboration, it is okay to say no.
And again, like, maybe one way or the other is better, maybe one way or the other is more natural
to you. But big picture, it is okay to say no. If somebody is asking for more and more and more,
or if somebody is telling you, you know, like, this needs to be done next, you know, this week,
I have a grant deadline. But the initial expectation that you outlined was next month.
You don't need to work nights. And you don't need to drop all your other things necessarily,
like again, hopefully you have a relationship with your boss or your mentor, you know, whatever
that you can figure this out together. But like, just because a difficult person says,
do this thing, like, oftentimes, sometimes the right response, like it is just okay to say no,
that is not the expectation we set. I cannot do that for you. Period.
Putting it in writing. So sort of directly follows up with what Beth said, like putting it in writing
is both a way that you can make it very clear. So if you have a hard time with this
in conversation, like in a meeting, right, somebody's like, I need you to do this thing,
and we're talking face to face, and it can be a little bit overwhelming to try to be direct
to them and say no to them. Putting it in writing is a great way to do it.
And it's a way then you can point back. If they push further, like, I'm sorry,
as per my previous email, I cannot do this. I already told you this, and you can say this
all very nicely. But I already told you, it's still a no. And as Beth said, like putting it
in writing is a great way to then get help from some sort of mentor champion protector,
that can look at it and say, yeah, good job, or let's soften it a little bit, or you know what,
no, you can be more assertive on this and help you say the word no in the way that it should
be said in the situation. And finally, it is okay to end collaborations. Of course, this all depends
on the scenario and situation. Sometimes this is a very hard thing, especially if you don't have
the support of a boss that is set up a collaboration, you know, there's lots of scenarios. But we really
hope for you that you can be in a situation where you can go to the champion and say, you know what,
this just does not work for me. This person's style doesn't work for me. This setup doesn't work for me.
I am being hurt in this situation. I'm not able to do my best work in this situation. I feel
uncomfortable in this situation, whatever it is. And then the answer is no to the collaboration.
And we have done that before. We have wrapped up collaborations and then said, thank you.
We are not interested in processing the next batch. Like, thank you. We're done with this.
That's okay.
And it's not often, but it is sometimes, you know, the best thing for everybody
is this set of people working together is not producing functional collaboration.
Yeah. Yeah. You know, obviously, like we try to avoid this point. And again, the tools we've got in
the first two talks in this series, hopefully, will help you avoid reaching this point. But I think
particularly trainees, people earlier in their careers end up feeling less able to say no,
less like they have less agency to be in these sorts of situations. And again, I hope for you
that you can find a situation where you have a boss, a mentor, somebody that can help you
not go forward, you know, end situations that really are not tenable, because you shouldn't
end up being stuck in that situation. And if the, you know, if you feel that way, again, like,
go find a mentor, someone else in this list, right, that there are, or a different list,
expand this list, let us know who else should be in this list. Because there should be somebody
there for you to help you with these difficult situations and to help be your champion to get
you out of these difficult situations if you're feeling trapped in them.
And I just want to sort of say, if you're getting towards the point where you feel like
ending it, even if you haven't put in some of the things that Erin talked about at the beginning,
some of the tools, like, it's never too late to try to get back on the same page.
Well, it's sometimes too late. It can take a while, but you can always see if something can be
corrected. But if you feel like there's not, you've done everything, you've used all the tools,
you've talked to all the people, and you're just never going to be back on the same page,
then ending it is how you protect yourself. Yeah. Yeah. And, you know, protecting,
I mean, even, yeah, protect yourself. I mean, I guess that's, you know, an important,
important thing that we try and emphasize in our lab all the time, right? Like, the people that work
in our lab are human. And their human needs are important, right? And sometimes, particularly at
some stages in your career, like, in some lab situations, it may end up feeling like
humans are treated more like a cog in a machine. And we don't want that to be true for anyone.
And so somewhat buried in here, I guess, is a little pep talk, like that. You should be treated
like a human, regardless of your career stage, regardless of your lab. And if you are not,
hopefully, you can find the support you need to help you be treated like a human again.
Really important. Thank you so much for putting that together.
Yeah. Yeah, my pleasure. I think, you know,
it's, it's funny, I feel like this is less of a, I mean, I had lots of tools,
again, watch the previous talks, but, you know, almost feels like this turns into more of a
therapy session than, you know,
Nothing wrong with a different therapy session.
Yeah. Yeah. But, but again, I think that's something that we really, really emphasize in our lab that
is not emphasized in all labs, in all situations, in or out of science, right? But if, I don't know,
I'm just going to start repeating myself. I want everybody in the world to be in a happy,
healthy, productive environment in which they can be respected as humans and grow the skills they
want to grow while being treated in, you know, a respectful manner, period. Amen.
Yeah. Thank you. You are, you are a great advocate for those folks, for all the ones that I,
that we know personally, and I think this will help some folks. Maybe don't have great advocates
close to hand. I hope so. I hope so. And anyone out there, if you have other tools or ideas,
like please do let, let us know. Leave a comment or, you know, drop, drop some info in the,
in the Ask Erin Dearbeth episode request. We would, I would love to dive more into this. Like,
I really, I really like caring for the human part of the scientist. So any other ideas or
resources you all have, like, please share. All right. Bye.