Hey Beth! Hey Erin, how are you?
Peachie keen, it is so good to see your lovely face this morning.
Always great to see you as well. Wonderful. Well I thought
that it was about time that we talk about just give an overview about the Cell Painting Assay
because it's something I feel like we've name dropped at least a handful of times at this point
but haven't actually said what what is the Cell Painting Assay? I can't believe we've gotten this
far into the podcast and never actually done that. That's crazy. Yeah, yeah it's it's funny
because it's really I mean I'd say like it's our bread and butter in our lab in in that like
something we do a lot you know run the image analysis of the the Cell Painting Assay for
lots of collaborators and you know the most latest protocol paper was simony at all and you know we've
been we are heavily involved in the Cell Painting Assay but like we should probably talk about
what it actually is. Is it making cells look beautiful like my background here?
I mean that's certainly part of it. Not that you know not that cells aren't beautiful in
their own native state but we do we do add some more color to make them even more visibly beautiful.
Yeah so to keep this quick because you know we're always able to give a long answer to anything
but to make this brief a brief introduction to Cell Painting so Cell Painting was originally
developed by Anne Carpenter in collaboration with Stuart Shreiber's lab and the it's a single
specific assay that is a high content assay and you can sort of one way to think about it is the
omics of morphology so it is a way of doing high throughput assay and looking at cells so morphology
being shape of cells and getting answers at the other end and so this is a schematic that I
stole from a recent slide deck of Ann's so I think this is you know pieced together from
several different publications and resources at this point but most recently stolen from an Ann
Carpenter slide deck and but I think a pretty basic overview of what this is as a concept for
the Cell Painting Assay you take cells they can be healthy cells they can be diseased cells
they can be cell culture sometimes they're on patient derived cell lines and then
generally we add a treatment that can be drugs drug screening is probably the most common use
for the Cell Painting Assay particularly this is an assay that's done in lots of pharma companies
for early stage drug discovery and so very easy for you know high content drug screening but also
very much also used academically with genetic treatments and it's done in a high content manner
so generally the cells are grown in well in an academic lab 384 well plates I know that in pharma
that have robots more robots you end up with you know higher density plates yeah we don't you know
we don't have lots of robots available to us in most of our academic collaborations other than
what we can awkwardly do ourselves and so you grow lots of cells lots of and most importantly
like lots of different treatment conditions then a specific staining panel that I'll get to
in the next slide but where we are adding dyes that are so so the Cell Painting Assay was optimized
to be cheap and easy and so we fix cells and then drop drop dyes into you know in with them so
and it labels a bunch of cellular compartments then we do image analysis
where we are identifying individual cells and making a bunch of measurements and then what you
end up with is downstream data that is much like you would get with any omics experiment
where you have a single cell is each row in this matrix and columns that in our case are morphological
features so there's some way of describing the cell if you think of other sorts of omics like
proteomics you would have the columns would be proteins and the values would be the amount of
that protein in the cell so in our case it's some value some mathematical description of
you know of a feature that's describing the morphology of a cell and these stains in it
can I ask a question absolutely so you've used the word or the term high content a couple times so
does that relate to the fact that there's just lots and lots of features here so we're doing
sort of many features all at once yes so we're measuring I mean so I can definitely
yes that is definitely one important part of this we are we'd say like measure everything ask
questions later so we are measuring hundreds two thousands of features the current you know
Cell Painting protocol is thousands although there's very you know variations
also we think of like high so high content and high throughput being sometimes sort of intermingled
where we also are doing this you know having the perturbations the different treatment conditions
are also at scale like sort of as as large as a reasonable depending on you know the skill level
of your technician or your robot again depending on who's doing this assay so you know both of those
we are measuring as many conditions as we can and as many features as we can sort of all in
once so this is a lot of data all at once so big times big equals real big real big yep yep
that's bad as math that I can do in my head too big times big real big love that one you know
and then this final little bit of the panel is just to illustrate you can then do any sort of
biological discovery that you would do on an omics level experiment you can look at relationships
between perturbations you can look at you know however you would handle omics data you can do
that on Cell Painting data so that's sort of the big picture of the experiment and then the
details of what we're actually looking at so this is from one of the earlier Cell Painting
papers but we have uh you know so this is a single example of a single condition a single cell line
um you know I'll put the asterisk of coming up in a future episode at some point you know we get
asked like oh how can you modify the Cell Painting Assay like what what can you do to change it and
we'll have an episode on that coming up in the future you know the punchline is whatever
you want basically it still works so spoiler alert but this is an example of a single cell line
and the standard panel of of dies that are labeling the standard panel of cellular structures
so it's this is like any generic wide field microscope where we have five channels
and we put in six stains and they measure eight or the and they label eight cellular
compartments in those channels and so here you see you know we have nucleus endoplasmic
reticulum so okay so nucleus is stained with hoaxed although again yeah i'm not going to
go into what what you can swap that's a whole other episode right i'm staying on target staying on
task here you can do it i believe in you yeah so we have endoplasmic reticulum stained with
concanavalin a nucleoli and cytoplasmic RNA that we see with cytoh actin which we see with
phylloidin and the Golgi and plasma membrane which we see with wheat germ aglutinin and
mitochondria that we see with mitotracker and so that is the standard like a lot that's a lot of
different cellular parts that we're seeing here labeled and again this is optimized to be
just all dyes that you just drop in without any you know awful fixation conditions for for getting
stuff that you know none of the none of the very complicated things you might do to to label specific
proteins or or specific molecules within the cell and then there are a couple pipelines
that we run they are CellProfiler pipelines is standard and we'll drop you know have links in
the show notes available you know our our current optimized pipelines one of them we start with
making illumination correction function which like for flat field correction and so we see um
depending on your microscope there are you know in this example like pretty heavily vignetting
so the corners are darker than the center so we do some math then we have another episode of
ask Erin Dear Beth all about this so we'll link that too to figure out how to correct that so
that the corners are no longer dark so that if you are measuring differences in intensities between
a cell in the middle of the image and a cell in the corner of the image differences are actually
due to biology not due to location in the picture yeah that would that would make things hard yes
yeah so we do that then we do assay dev assay development which is just refining
the parameters you need to segment nuclei and cell bodies and so here's that we also have another
ask Erin Dear Beth episode about how we do this at scale that shows so many episodes
I know I know so I can you know we'll have this link in show notes as well showing how
what we do you know in again like at scale with high content high you know lots of data finding
making sure that we have good segmentation across all of our data but uh it means you know
tweaking a little bit because depending on the batch depending on the cell line depending on the
you know just the day on the microscope uh you might need to change your parameters a tiny bit
to get the most accurate nuclei and cell segmentations but once we've optimized that
then we run an analysis pipeline so this is a CellProfiler pipeline just wanted to highlight
that here we have in green like this is find our objects and all of these pink boxes are make
measurements so we have you know measurements on the images themselves to get some basic information
on the image these are all images measurements that we make on the objects so we're making
measurements on the nuclei on the cells and on the cytoplasm which is cell minus nucleus
so lots of object measurements this likewise is some specific handling for the mito stain to get
some mito mitochondria specific measurements and this is for looking specifically at the
background of images measuring some further you know image information about that so we you
know potentially you can use that for qc or or other such things so just lots of measurements
are made and this is an example of what comes out so we have yeah that's that's kind of scary
yeah so this is you know this is a tiny little crop of a you know a single csv opened up an excel
here where each row is a cell and we have actually thousands of features going going across um
but you can see these are you know features measured in the cell in the nucleus in the cytoplasm
and we'll have another episode coming up very soon talking about like how do you actually
understand these feature names that's another thing but uh and we and we actually have a
workflow for how do we take these you know these individual numbers that we have measured in these
objects and how do we make profiles right which is to say it involves some normalization it
involves aggregation to say you know for if i'm doing a you know for this drug what is the
set of features and numbers the vector as you you know if you're thinking mathematically that
describes this drug treatment because we have you know thousands of single cells and we need to
you know of measurements made in many compartment thousands of measurements thousands of single
cells we want to condense them into something that is not really big times really big so
slightly smaller than really big times really big to be able to to work downstream and so that
is just like our big picture overview uh my big picture overview i did all of the talking here sorry
that anything else you wanted to add in about the Cell Painting Assay big picture no i think the
only thing i would say is make it even one picture bigger which is there's tons of great assays
out there if you know exactly what you want to find like if you know that you care about
phosphosome protein like that's great you should measure phosphosome protein but what this lets you
do is kind of just find your unknown unknowns like i'm not sure exactly which proteins connect with
one another or which patient samples look like each other like let's do something that's instead of
really specific really broad and catch as many connections as possible so that's where it kind
of differs from a lot of other assays you might usually think about yeah absolutely absolutely
and i think that's a great point that it's it's sort of the you know exploring the unknown space
um at more you know much more general discovery than asking which then you can dive into and ask
more specific questions once you're in deep diving but it's not set it's set up to capture
as broad uh so you're certainly missing specific things with this assay like this does not capture
every single you know every single part of a cell like smells so pretty complex i don't know if
anybody else has picked up on that yet but you know but you are capturing a sort of optimized
view as broad of you as possible yeah totally great point awesome well thank you for that
fantastic overview yeah yeah and uh yeah thanks for thanks for joining me along on this again
now and then i have a an episode we can point to you know the next 400 times we name drop the
Cell Painting Assay indeed this might be one of our better linked ones yes yeah awesome well talk to
you later babes bye
you