Hello, Erin!
Hello, Beth!
Lovely to see you, my dear.
It is great to see you, always!
What are we going to talk about today?
So I thought I would talk a little bit about data and metadata.
I know that's one of your favorite things to talk about.
And this is actually a talk that I gave at CZI a few months back, but when I was talking
with friends there, they were like, this is the sort of information that is actually useful.
And I think a lot of people don't understand in terms of like, how do we actually put data
together for deep learning models and like what kind of data is useful for deep learning
models and how does metadata change that?
So I thought that was a topic worth covering.
That sounds lovely and helpful and interesting.
I mean, you think everything that has metadata is interesting, so you might be slightly biased.
I will admit admittedly more than a little biased, yes.
All right.
Well, hopefully it is useful and helpful and interesting for others as well.
But what I was asked to talk about at this conference was about adopting data from new
imaging technologies.
So if we're talking about adopting data from imaging technologies and making it work for
deep learning, the question I'm always going to start with asking is, what do you want
your deep learning model to do?
Because it turns out deep learning models can do a lot of different things.
They can do activity prediction.
They can be used for virtual staining.
Most commonly they're used for segmentation, but there's a whole lot of things and exactly
what you want your deep learning model to do will determine the data that you need for
it.
That makes sense?
Yeah.
But so we've talked a lot as a field, not so much really on the podcast, but certainly
a lot in the field about collecting lots of data and data repositories.
And we've talked about the idea on this whole painting gallery for sure.
But as there's this push to deposit your data, deposit your data, your data is only probably
actually useful if it has biology I know that I care about and I understand how your
image works, a.k.a. if it's annotated with good metadata, or if I'm making a big foundation
model.
And we'll talk a bit about what actually a foundation model means in a minute.
Yeah.
I think it fits nicely with my hot take that data without metadata is useless.
That's my fight me statement.
Yeah.
I mean, it's useless for case one.
It can be useful for case two.
But case one is way more common.
Case one is way more common and I'll still fight.
I'll still fight on that statement.
That's my...
That's fine.
You can fight whoever you want.
I am not here to stop you from fighting people.
Okay.
I have big feelings when it comes to metadata.
We'll just leave it at that.
I think everybody who watches the podcast knows that at this point.
I think that we all know and love your love of metadata.
So if I can align your data to my data, there are lots of interesting approaches.
And this is some preliminary data from work that we're doing in the lab about trying to
align data taken on two different microscopes and use clever features of deep learning
models.
I won't talk too much about what this is because this work is still in preparation.
But there are things we can do if we know how your data lines up with my data.
And I say that a little bit flippantly.
There's often things we can do.
It's not always that there are things we can do.
Being able to align even data that we know should align.
So this is a figure from John Revolo's paper describing some of the jump data sets and
some of the benchmarks he put together out of the jump data sets.
Even in cases where we know we should be able to align the data together.
In this case, we have data of the same plate of compounds that was then subdivided and
distributed to many companies who were all using the exact same lot of cells and the
exact same lot of dies to create images.
If we tried to align everybody's data to each other, the goodness of data alignment,
which you should read, goodness of data alignment as like individual distinct colored blobs in
the top row, is really different even just across different batch alignment methods that
the field agrees are good.
And we can see that in some cases are lower things, which is like essentially which set
of hands or robots made the data and what microscope did they make it on.
In some cases that is predominating and the data is not well mixed.
So I'm being a little bit flippant when I say we can totally do it if we can align our
data to your data.
That's still a hard problem, but smart people are working hard on it.
So I want to not say that it's going to be easy to align to somebody else's data, but
it often can be done.
But again, we can only do that.
The technical things are going to get worked out and smart people are working hard.
They can't be worked out fully if the data isn't fair and annotated with metadata.
So what do I mean by fair?
You probably heard this term several times at this point, I certainly hope.
Findable accessible, intrapropable, reproducible and reusable.
And the F here is really important.
The data has to be findable.
We have to be able to know what it is.
We have to be able to open it and access it.
And so in order to have the data be fair to be used, it has to be all of these things
or otherwise we can't use it.
We can't use it if we can't find it.
And right now a lot of our data repositories are sort of overrepresented with data from
places like the Broad where Erin and I work that make big data and the Allen Institute
and CSI Engine and other places that make gorgeous, huge, clean data.
But I would like to argue here in my Vibes graph that actually there's probably a lot
more data out there if we collect it from old biologists everywhere if only we could
compile it.
And so I think that we're missing out on actually a gazillion data sets that would be great
if we could collect them.
But we can't collect them fairly yet.
And so we currently can't use a lot of the data that's being made because we are lacking
this ability to have commonly annotated metadata that exists in fair repositories.
And just knowing that the data exists and making the data be findable is often the really
hard part there.
But having it be well annotated is not a trivial task and it's not like that the community
doesn't care about this and that's why this isn't done yet.
Some of which is like we have to figure out where all this data is going to live and data
storage is not inexpensive.
But also some of this is about the fact that microscopy is not actually just one thing.
There are many kinds of devices in a trench coat.
It is many modalities in a trench coat that we all call microscopes.
And some of you might have something that looks like any of these different devices
inside this trench coat.
So it is a really hard thing to come up with a set of metadata that everybody agrees on.
Again, smart people are working hard, but this is really non-turbial because some people
here are microscoping and they think electron microscope.
Some people think microscope and they think something where I'm capturing one molecule
at a time and some people are like confocal in a box that gives me hundreds of samples
per day.
And the metadata at the moment is a mess.
When we ask people how do you annotate your data, do you annotate it by color or by the
name of the dye or by what the dye is targeting or by what part of the cell the dye is targeting?
The answer we usually get is yes.
We as a field have not decided how we want to do this.
And so we as a field should start coming up with ways to do this.
I love this example because also none of these are actually wrong, which I think helps illustrate
what a hard issue this is.
Because it's not like any biologist giving you any of these answers is worse than the
other or these are all valid responses.
As a field, as those of us who are passionate about metadata, the challenge really becomes
how do we guide people to record the answer that we are looking for?
We need to ask a very specific question, not just what do you name it?
Here you have it in four different examples rather than just what's its name, what is
its color, what is the dye, the channel, etc.
And even me as the person who is doing this might care about different things on different
days.
If I want to check if I think that there is auto fluorescence that is coming in, I care
about the name or the color of the dye and the name because I can then figure out what
the color is.
But then if I want to know what is the biology of my sample, maybe I don't care which DNA
damage dye somebody used.
I just care that it is a DNA damage dye.
Maybe I don't care if somebody did phylloidin or an anti-actin antibody.
Maybe I just care that it is the actin.
So even the same person at two different points might care about two completely different
properties here.
Yes.
So we are working on it but there is still a long way to go because the question is hard.
And yeah, smart people are working hard.
This is a draft of a thing that people on the team such as Erin and a great former student
of hers, Guy Grbaka, have put together for trying to make this hierarchical.
But there is a lot of different versions of this at this point.
People are working on different ones and not everybody has agreed yet.
So we are working to come towards it as a community.
There is hope in sight.
So what about the other case?
The case where what can we do with the data if I am making a big foundation model?
Nobody agrees on what a foundation model is for the record.
So if you are not sure what people mean when they say foundation models, people generally
just mean model that works on lots of different stuff.
And I don't think we have come to a better definition as a field than that.
So mostly write explanations about what I mean.
We have a deep neural network where we have inputs come in and we have outputs come out.
They might be words, they might be measurements.
The inputs might be words or measurements or things.
The diversity of neural networks now is insane and this is sort of depicting probably something
that is meant to be convolutional neural network and there are whole many flavors now.
But this is at its heart the basic idea.
And in a deep neural network we have neurons that talk to each other that are grouped into
layers and they might connect to each other in complex fashions.
And that's really all that this means is we have individual sort of algorithms that might
fire if like the sum of all of these things is greater than a certain number.
This will put out a yes and if not it will put out a no.
And so this really was actually inspired by how neurons work and how brains work.
But the fact that we have all of these different connections that we can tune how important
they are is what makes deep neural networks so powerful.
There's a few emergent properties here from the fact that that is all we're doing is just
sort of changing the weights of those connections.
You'll sometimes hear people talk about weights and saying like okay based on those weights
you know do I get the right answer yes or no.
Because all we're doing is sort of randomly changing the weights we can't control what
the model learns.
It will find whatever associations we optimize for with our loss function which is what we're
trying to get the model to learn.
And whatever associations exist in our trading data.
One of the famous ones is like if an animal is standing on grass it's more likely to be
a dog than a cat because most pictures of animals on grass are dogs.
So it will learn associations that are in our data that maybe we never intended.
If it's not in the data we have no reason to believe it's going to be emergently learned.
It could be but there's no reason to believe that it is going that anything that the model
is spitting out that it's never seen before is true.
We have no reason to believe that that's true.
And the bigger the model the more complex the associations between our inputs and our
outputs the more data we need to check all of these and set the value of all of these
arrows to something reasonable.
In big models we routinely have billions of arrows here and billions is lots.
And so the way deep learning works is we in this case this is a convolutional like we
sort of say hey network take an image and then I want it to come out looking like this
go through the thing and see if it comes out looking like this.
If it doesn't change all of the sort of strength of those arrows that I had in my previous
slide and then try again and then try again and then try again and then try again and
our loss function our thing we're trying to get the model to learn is how similar are
these two images.
That's all deep learning is.
Now in order to know what the right answer is we need to have a right answer we need
to have a question that we can answer and having cell masks for good jillions of data
sets is the thing that we wish that we had but we certainly don't for most of biology.
So usually when people are doing things that are called foundation models these days they're
relying heavily on unsupervised learning which really isn't unsupervised so much as
we've come up with clever ways of getting around making our supervising data and not
really unsupervised.
A lot of times I hear people talk about self supervised data where we haven't had to beautifully
make ground truth by hand.
And so we can come up with the task that will make the network pretty good at stuff and then
just fine tune the arrows a little bit.
If we're sure that our arrows are close to right then we don't have to actually do that
much to change our arrows with our real data because our arrows are already pretty good
based on some like almost as good task.
So what do I mean what's a good example?
So like for the large language models of the world they didn't actually just sort of like
stick all the sentences in and say like okay I'm gonna like how did they train chat Jpt
for example so that what came out was actually sentences that made sense.
So it trained it on tasks like I'm gonna sort of omit a word guess what the missing word
should be.
This word should probably not be tennis.
If it gets tennis it's probably wrong compared to if it gets eat it's probably right.
Look would also probably it's probably less right but it's probably also right.
Tennis is also probably not the right word here.
Or they came up with sort of yes or no tasks that they could do easily and automatically
which is you know take pairs of sentences you know give it either the right or the wrong
second sentence and then say did the model and ask the model what is this the right second
sentence.
So that's something you can do in an automated fashion without a human having to sit there
and like come up with pairs of sentences.
So we can do this in bioimaging also by doing things like so this is from a version of dyno
which is an image transformer we can say all right I've taken the whole image and a crop
from an image is the crop from the same image yes or no.
And so we can get the model to say OK I get stuff about images I understand what images
are like without having to go through and manually make a bunch of data because we can
create crops randomly as we go.
And this is super powerful because it means we don't have to sit there sort of making
the right answers all the time but it means that we need tons of data and tons of compute.
So this was trained on 256 A 100s which were the state of the art for three days on billions
of data points when we talk about segment anything which underlies things like cell
post Sam and micro Sam and the first version was pretty good though it definitely was was
not perfect.
But this was 11 million images with one billion masks billion objects it took to do this.
And the only thing we're aware of this close in size is the painting gallery but that's
all one essay we don't have that for biology.
Like I said 250 GPUs for 68 hours.
It's the carbon equivalent of driving a car from me in Boston to Erin in Seattle and
back again just for one training run of this model.
And at the time those GPUs were like 10 grand a pop.
So like this is a couple million dollars worth of GPUs which your traditional academic lab
does not have.
I do not have two million dollars of GPUs in my lab if only.
Yeah no but yeah no I won't even go there but a girl can dream.
And we can take foundation models and we can reuse them in other clever ways and so foundation
models are doing what they've promised to do which is you train a big thing once and
then you can use it in lots of other applications.
And so we can start doing this with unlabeled image data by doing things like these dino
transformers but you know they're not everything and they often need to be tuned to exactly
and so one of the reasons we like self-post-sam is it does in our experience a good mix of
getting it pretty good on the first try but then being easily retrainable to exactly the
right thing.
So our conclusions are foundation models are going to need to have everything in them
we want to find the good the bad and the ugly so if we need them to handle ugly data they're
going to need to handle ugly data.
Most groups are not going to be able to train these yet so we need to sort of rely on having
good commercial collaborators or big national or international collaborations and we probably
don't have all the data that we're going to need for it yet.
They're going to be powerful because then even if you don't have the you know two and
a half million dollars in GPUs you can absolutely go forward and sort of make great things out
of these foundation models that can be smaller and lighter weight but if we don't keep collecting
all of the data and preferably annotating it things aren't going to advance as fast
as they could and so my argument and where I'll stop here is the way forward for now
is to hopefully make lots more fair data and make it possible to do this by having repositories
and having standardized metadata that biologists could contribute to.
We make it attractive for people to contribute to it by saying like hey look if you give
us your data you're going to have models that work on your data because they're part of
some big training set and we make it actually attractive to sort of we tell people what's
in it for them and just keep making clever and clever models with the smallest data that
we can and hope that these big commercial entities or our collaborative things come
together and we can keep making great big models that can then be sort of turned into
small clever models.
So that's really what the talk was about and I hope it is a useful overview of where we
are now in terms of like what bio-images can do and what we hope that they'll be able to
do even more going forward but what work we need to do to get there.
Yeah I think so.
I mean I think I don't know again a little biased over here but you know hearing that
tracking metadata and depositing images you know two things that I am very passionate
about actually I think you know did a lovely job of explaining why those are so important
and why I and you and many other people care so deeply about this.
Yeah well thanks for listening I hope it was it delivered but yeah please think about depositing
your data somewhere annotated whether that's the bio-image archive, IDR, the Selpington
Gallery we would love to have your data because we would love to make models that work for
you.
Awesome thanks Beth.
Thanks.