Hey Erin!
Hello Beth!
Good to see ya!
Always a pleasure.
Always enjoy podcast day.
I wanted to just quickly talk today about a resource that was made by bioimaging North
America as well as our team called the Bioimaging Guide that I think and hope is super helpful
for helping people realize what they don't know they don't know about bioimage analysis.
Yeah, that's a good one.
And bioimaging in general.
Yeah.
So obviously we'll put the links for this in the show notes but this is the Bioimaging
Guide.
So this is actually the companion to a paper that a whole bunch of fantastic people led
by a couple of former postdocs in the imaging platform, Rebecca and Barbara, but a ton of
names you've probably seen before, great folks who put this together.
Here's the major take home if you learn nothing else.
A lot of people spend a lot of time going back and forth between sample preparation
and image acquisition and they optimize these two things back and forth a lot.
And then once they're happy with this, they start thinking about image analysis and then
once they're happy with this, they start thinking about data interpretation.
And that actually makes your life a lot harder than it needs to be.
If you do image analysis as soon as you can, as soon as your images seem kind of reasonable,
you might actually pick up on artifacts or things that you could fix at the sample preparation
or the image acquisition stage that you didn't know were going to be a problem until you
started trying to put your analysis together or until you started looking at your thinking
about what are the statistics I'm going to present.
So the sooner you put this whole cycle together and the more feedback you let there be between
the steps, the better your experiment is going to go and the more likely that you're going
to get data that helps you at the end.
Yeah, absolutely.
And I think lots of people who are trained as wet lab biologists doing the sample prep
and the image acquisition is the thing that is most comfortable to them.
I think don't think about the image analysis and data interpretation part of also having
that same sort of iterative cycle.
We will do assay development.
We will start with a rough pipeline and then we will refine it and then we will make sure
it's giving the outputs that we can use to do the biological statistics that we want
to do.
But that is a place that receives just as much iteration as the image acquisition and
sample prep.
And so thinking sort of in that, expanding your framework of thought to include image
analysis is not just, okay, I've done all of the images.
Now we go make this one holy grail perfect pipeline to extract data.
That's not how it works.
Yeah.
And if it is how it works, then you might miss out on the chance to say, oh, if I'd
actually switched from wide field to confocal, I could have done my analysis really easily,
but now my analysis is super hard.
You can actually do less image analysis by doing image analysis earlier often.
Yeah.
Because you can fix things at the sample prep and the image acquisition stage.
So I certainly hope you read this paper.
It was the hard work of a lot of people, but so what we wanted to do was to provide a high
level overview of here are all of the sort of major things to think about ahead of time
because often part of the reason that people sort of don't do these steps in order is not
because they're malicious.
It's because first they get taught to do this because this happens first and then they get
taught to do this and then they get taught to do this.
And so they weren't even, they didn't even know this was a thing while they were doing
this.
Like it's not that they're trying to do bad science.
They're not doing bad science.
They just don't know what they don't know.
Yeah, absolutely.
I think this also comes into play with our, like often a lot of what we do, I mean, we
are strictly image analysts.
We are not doing any wet lab prep.
So we have lots of collaborators that are doing just the sample prep and image acquisition.
And that's fine.
You know, if that, you know, that's their, you know, having separate skill sets and bringing
in collaborators is amazing and super important part of science.
But also everybody is happier and more successful when there is at least constant communication.
So if you're not doing the image analysis yourself, if you don't want, you know, if
you don't have the time and space and opportunity to develop all of those skills on your own,
there should at the very least be a constant conversation between, you know, experts in
any one arm of their, you know, sometimes we even then get involved with experts in statistics
because we have some basic knowledge of statistics from what we do, but we're not experts in it.
And so, you know, likely you are more comfortable in one of these corners than the other.
And so having lots of communication from the beginning, lots of planning from the beginning
with the collaborator that is more expert in any one given area will also make this
all so much better, even if you're not doing it all yourself.
Yeah.
I'm sure there's someone out there who's incredibly comfortable in all four, but there's probably
like one person.
Yeah.
Like most people, it's like one, maybe two.
So anyway, this is a awesome paper.
Please do read it.
It's got sort of things of like how you might think through some stuff.
It's got a glossary.
And it has a list of resources.
And the major thing that we worried about, because we've written papers like this before,
is the second that you make a list of resources.
Somebody publishes a new great resource and now your resources are out of date.
The other thing that we weren't incredibly excited about is a paper has to have a certain
scholarly tone to it.
And sometimes we're more interested in a conversational friendly tone instead.
You know, there's this place for all of these things.
And so while we were writing the paper, we said, we don't want to just write a paper.
We want there to also be a website version of this, a website version where we can be
a little more conversational.
We can have a few more discussions and we can keep it up to date and keep adding new
things that we like.
And so this is bioimagingguide.org.
It's the companion website to this paper.
And what it isn't is an exhaustive list of all resources.
What it isn't is, you know, a three semester, you know, course sequence on here's how you
learn to do all of these things because people have already done great work.
It's a lot of great work out there.
But what we wanted to do is in the same thing as the paper, just give you a high level list
of like, here's what's out there here, the major things you probably want to know about.
And then give you a way to learn it.
And so here again is that same figure.
But so each section sort of starts with an introduction.
Why is this thing important?
What does this contribute?
And it's based around the same four quadrants that were in that figure.
And each section ends with resources for learning more.
Those resources might be papers.
They might be websites.
They might be textbooks.
They might be videos.
And so what we've really tried to do here is say, here's the overall basic idea.
These are the major things you should think about.
And here are experts you can go talk to.
Sometimes these are the links to sort of societies.
You can check out our podcast episode on some of the different societies we like
and the conferences that they have where you can go and learn more.
Because my team is an image analysis team, we've put a lot of time into the image analysis
part of the book.
And this is one of my favorite parts.
And so it has things like, what is this thing?
How do I measure it?
Where can things go wrong?
Where can I learn more about this?
And we try wherever we can to sort of say, oh yeah, like, here's an analogy.
You know, here's something to just sort of make this a little bit easier.
And so if you try to read a paper like that and, you know, it's just not getting through,
we hope this guide will be a sort of more intuitive and nice way.
And if you think there's something missing, we have a Google form where you can suggest
and say like, hey, you know what's not in here that I think would be really helpful.
Like either here's a particular paper I think is cool that you should add or, you know,
you haven't covered this.
And that's really confusing to me.
We can't promise we'll do it immediately.
We absolutely welcome you to actually just write stuff for the book.
Anyone can write for the book.
But you absolutely can also just say like, I really feel like this is missing.
I don't know it well enough to teach it, but I want to learn it.
And if the reason that you're having difficulty figuring out some of this stuff
is because maybe English isn't your first language,
which for the majority of the people in the world it is not.
We've worked with some great scientists in doing this.
In different parts of who are from different parts of the world originally,
and some of them still to start translating the guide into other languages.
So here is the bio-imaging guide in Spanish.
Right now, besides English, it's available in Spanish, Portuguese and Czech.
We are happy to work with folks.
If you think this is super cool and you want to help us correct AI translations
into good actual translations, we're totally happy to work with you to get this book
in whatever language you want it to be.
Just email me.
There's a link on the page.
But if nothing else, what I hope you take away from this episode is
it's really critical to help to come up with these sort of plans
and understand the whole experiment before you finish some of the parts
and realize that now you might actually need to redo them.
But you don't need to know everything right away.
If you just get a sense of what you don't know and who to talk to,
then there are resources out there to help you find the right person to talk to
and they can help you do the best experiment possible.
Absolutely.
Yeah, the you don't know what you don't know is such a hard thing to overcome in any field,
in any area.
And so it's so great to have a resource here built around that question of just letting
you understand better.
What don't you already know that you might need or want to become expert in or find a friend
who is expert in?
Awesome.
Thanks for hanging out.
I hope that was useful.
We hope you like the book.
We hope you give us more stuff that you want to learn in it.
And thanks for hanging out.
Thank you.