Hello Beth.
Hello Erin, always lovely to see you.
I agree.
Yeah, so recently we actually gave a quick overview, well as quick as I'm able to do
when I'm talking about it.
Of the Cell Painting Assay.
And so today I thought it would be interesting to dive into like what do Cell Painting features
mean.
There's a lot of discussion in particularly, you know, right now in morphological profiling,
which again as I sort of said in the Cell Painting episode is kind of like the omics
of looking at cell shape that we're doing in Cell Painting Assay.
And.
And intensity and textures and crazy.
Yes, yes, absolutely.
Yeah.
But in our, I mean, I think in probably in every field, but I can only speak knowledgeably
about our particular field, you know, there's lots of discussion at the moment of like,
okay, everybody wants to do deep learning.
And one of the major drawbacks of many deep learning techniques is that the features that
come out at the end that are, you know, describing your condition are not interpretable.
And so the Cell Painting Assay and the sort of more traditional features that we're getting
out of CellProfiler are quite interpretable.
And so I thought it would be helpful though to kind of like dive into the feature names
and explain like, great, people say, oh yeah, CellProfiler is interpretable, but like,
how do we actually interpret them?
Let's look at them.
So yeah, with that, I am sharing here, this is a page in, so the 2023 Simony Nature Protocols
paper was a giant work led by my dear, dear Beth right here.
That was optimizing the Cell Painting Assay.
So this is the second time that we had a major protocol paper published on the Cell Painting
assay.
But here in this repository, and we'll drop the Lincoln show notes, we have a wiki that
has just sort of some extra like casual, more casual information about the Cell Painting
assay.
And one of the things we have in here is what do Cell Painting features even mean?
And so I thought this was just a great thing to like scroll through chat through and explain
what they mean.
Well, and because I mean capable of taking credit for anything, this is basically copied
verbatim from like the wiki for the Cell Painting v2 paper and was built over like many years
by lots of people.
This is not a thing that I personally made.
But it is a really great resource that the lab has made over the years.
Yes.
Yeah.
All right, fine.
You can refuse to take credit, sole credit on this.
Didn't mean to, but yeah, did not mean to imply this was all the last work because so
many fabulous, wonderful scientists have worked to lead us to this point.
Yes.
But it is in a repository for the paper that that led.
So that is true.
I'm just I'm just putting that out there.
Okay.
Here we go.
So if you need a refresher on the Cell Painting Assay, you know, go go check out the that episode
will drop it in in show notes.
But basically, we as a reminder, we have pictures of cells.
We identify nuclei.
We identify cell bodies.
We define the cytoplasm, which is the cell minus the nucleus.
And then there are a number of channels that we are making measurements in.
So we are identifying the cell, for example, and then making a whole series of measurements
using that same object.
So one thing I want to emphasize here is that the object that we are identifying, we may
use some comBINAtion of channels for identifying like a cell object.
But then that object is independent of the channels that we used to identify it.
It is just now like a mathematical squiggle, right?
And we're saying, okay, now I can place that squiggle on top of any of these images and
make measurements about what is inside that squiggle.
Sorry, in any of, yeah, in any of these images independently of what I used to create that
cell object.
Yeah, that's a super important point to emphasize.
Yeah.
So we have these five channels.
We give them names.
Usually we name them based on what we are looking at, the expected structure.
So DNA, RNA, ER, mito, AGP, standing for actin, Golgi, and plasma membrane.
So that is our description for the image itself, because it's the structure that we are expecting
to see in that image based on the stain that should be showing in that channel that we
imaged.
We have, right, so then many, many, many measurements, thousands of measurements.
And yeah, this is an older version, because back then we were only doing like 2000 features,
and now we tend to do closer to like 8000.
Yeah.
And it's kind of, it's kind of nuts.
All the things.
I like it.
Yeah.
So we then, again, we take measurements in individual channels, in the different objects,
and then we can also make extra measurements, right, that are features looking at the relationship
between channels.
So that's an extra set where we then have correlation features that then are describing
multiple channels, the mathematical relationship between information and multiple images within
those objects.
So yeah, I mentioned we have the cells, the cytoplasm and the nuclei as our objects, and
then we have a bunch of categories of features that we're measuring.
So these are links to the CellProfiler documentation telling you more details about the exact measurements
in each of these categories.
But just to note, you know, there are different categories of measurements, and they can be
things such as shape, area shape, describing, that's not actually looking at fluorescent,
you know, pixel intensities, it's telling you just about the shape itself, but then
something like intensity, like that's telling us all about pixel intensities within that
shape, and often includes things that are quite simple, like the total intensity or
the mean pixel intensity within there.
But it can also be more complex, like talking about the distribution or the patterns of
those intensities.
So sort of a full range of like very easily understandable to like, actually I can wave
my hands and tell you what it's doing, but it's, but digging into the very specifics
is complicated.
And then some of these, like texture and granularity, again, are quite easily on a sort of conceptual
level of we're looking at how much texture is in an image.
And you know, granularity is if I erode a part of the image, you know, a piece at a
time, how much is left.
So it's also kind of like a very similar to a texture conceptually, but mathematically
quite different.
And mathematically, you know, so we get the sort of like the biologist hand waving, oh,
it's looking at texture, but in terms of like, what does that mean?
You know, there's a bit of a disconnect.
Likewise.
So I think also talking about interpretability, like these all are interpretable in that we
can tell you the exact math.
So lots of deep learning is a black box of what math is happening here.
We can tell you the exact math, like you can go to the CellProfiler code, you can look
and see like what are numbers.
Yeah, if you really want to, you know, what numbers go in and what numbers come out.
Um, and, but a biologist is going to have a much easier time telling you like, oh, cell
area, like I know exactly what that means.
At first it's like, oh, the granularity, you know, of this structure in this, you know,
like it gets a little more hand wavy what that could actually mean.
So, but so that is, we have these feature categories, different kinds of measurements.
Um, also some of them have extra things tacked on the end.
Um, so like, Xernikis, those are a math, a math for describing.
I was going to say, maybe we should do a Xerniki episode someday, but no, we probably should
not.
Maybe you could do a Xerniki episode.
Um, I mean, I do think like, I think that would actually be awesome.
It's, it's really interesting what he's doing.
I understand it to the level of it's telling us, you know, how, how things are, it is math
that tells us like how things were arranged.
Um, I think that's all you need to know.
I think you just did the Xerniki episode.
Congratulations.
Um, but so, you know, some features, right, have different parameters at the very end
of the feature name saying like, okay, this is, um, additional, additional pieces of information
and you need to know mathematically, you know, to understand the math.
Um, so like the scale at which these things are measured.
Um, so that is like how we get to these features in a nutshell.
And then, um, I just wanted to show like, I can show you really quickly.
Um, just a few examples, you know, of, we can just dive into a couple of features here.
Um, do, do, do.
So, um, you know, here is opening an Excel.
So it's not the most beautiful, but if we, okay, see, I know, ah, there we go.
Um, to make this readable, you know, just picking some random features here.
Um, again, this is just totally at random, but the way that we under, so all of the
Excel profiler features are named in a consistent way.
So we, it starts by telling you what compartment, um, this was what object this was measured in.
So we measured it in the object we call the cells.
Then this is the category, um, of measurement that we made.
So we made a texture measurement.
This is the specific measurement that we made.
I don't know what an info measurement one is necessarily other than it is one math.
So just for the texture.
Um, then it's telling us the name of the image that we measured it in.
So again, we named this image actin because it was the structure that we expected to see
given our stains.
You could name it what you can name it whatever.
There's many ways that one could name, but this is our standard for the Cell Painting.
Um, and then this is just some extra parameters that have to do with the info measure one.
Oh, this is a fun example.
And this leads right into why don't I want to say, okay, so this is saying, um, within the nuclei.
Um, we measured an intensity feature.
That specific feature is the standard deviation of the intensity at the edge of the object.
And we measured it in the actin channel.
But wait, you might say there shouldn't be any actin within the nucleus.
What?
That doesn't make any sense.
And so here I think this is a really important point that I want to make, um, about, uh, about
CellProfiler features.
So we will get questions about this.
Like, okay, but how is that interpretable?
You can't interpret actin in the nucleus.
There is no actin within the nucleus.
But wait a little bit, but you shouldn't be effected and shouldn't be fluid.
And we should not see effected within the nucleus.
So what I want to point out is here, this beautiful illustration, I clearly spent hours on, you know,
um, I love it.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
You know, not to scale, but if we think of, we have an objective and we have a cell growing
on a cover slip and what, you know, so cells, even the beautiful, even cell
cells that are beautiful for microscopy that like pancake out nice and flat for imaging,
even those kinds of cells, they are in three dimensions.
Um, yeah, like, whoa, we don't live in flatland cells are three dimensional.
Um, so what that means is, um, in this example, I have blue nucleus and I have some cellular
compartment we can pretend it's ER, you know, that's like perinuclear here.
Um, I mean, it's red, so it's the mitochondria, but sure.
I know.
Okay.
Right.
I know.
My nose is red.
Um, so, you know, uh, it's some unknown cellular structure here.
Um, yeah.
But if we look at that from the top, what we see is that, um, so we have, you know,
can clearly see the nucleus is this nice round thing here in the middle of the cell from
the top, the majority of the signal.
Yes.
The majority of this red is going to show up as in a circle around the nucleus, but
because the cell is three dimensional, there is actually some structure that when we are,
you know, looking sort of the top view or I guess a bottom view, because we have a bottom
here, bottom view of the cell, um, you know, you do see some of this compartment that is
outside of the cell, um, looks like it's overlapping with the nucleus.
And so when we're looking at features here, these measured features, so hooks tends to
be a very nice tight stain that doesn't drift cytoplasmically.
So we'll see, you know, the intensity of our DNA within the cell.
We basically see nothing.
And if we look at the intensity of the DNA within the nucleus, it's very, very bright.
And if we look here at my pretend ER, that even though it's ER should be, you know,
green and my door, red, bear with me.
So I have very particular feelings about what color different organ.
I know it's kind of ridiculous, but also like, yeah, it is what it is.
Um, so then if we look in the cell, we see, right, like clearly that makes sense.
We see the ER here is mostly perinuclear.
Like that's biologically true.
But then if I look at features in measured in the nucleus, right, because it is this,
you know, it is this object that is a circle of a, you know, a three dimensional
compressed thing.
Like we're seeing some of this stain is actually, actually there in our nucleus
object, which doesn't reflect completely real biology, you know, nucleus, like in the
cell, we don't have endoplasmic reticulum inside of the nucleus in a cell.
But our stain, because we're going from 3D to 2D measurements, we will measure some
there.
So that's how to interpret.
If you get this sort of nonsensical feature, um, well, yeah, go back.
Can you go back to the, I just want to make one microscopy point, which is like, and
some of this has to do with sort of how thick of what's called an optical section that
we're taking.
Yeah.
So we tend to do Cell Painting in wide field, though you can't do it in either
wide field or confocal.
And what that means is if I draw on Erin's lovely drawing here with my
annotator, um, with wide field microscopy, you don't tend to get a lot of Z
resolution.
You tend to take light from a lot of different Z points in your sample.
And so that's why we have this effect.
If we really, really, really, really, really only wanted a very thin one, if we
did something like confocal microscopy, we could take a thinner Z section and then
we wouldn't see much or at all of this stuff that's on top of the nucleus.
Um, but for Cell Painting, we typically want to gather as much information as possible.
And so that's why generally we prefer to use wide field so that we get more of
the stuff, even if it makes it a little bit more jumbled, because we're seeing a
three thing compressed into 2d, but it is totally possible to take a thin section
where this doesn't happen.
If that's what you want for whatever asset you're doing.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
Good point.
And, you know, we can go, like, we'll also coming up soon have an episode about, like,
how can you modify the Cell Painting Assay and, you know, and talk about wide
field versus confocal.
Um, but in terms of, you know, what is our, our standard Cell Painting Assay is
wide field.
So we are getting all of this extra, all of this extra information, but like, again,
great point.
It could be handled differently such that you could, um, end up.
With, you know, with different, a different way of imaging here.
Um, this is just not what we're usually working with.
Um, yeah.
It's a great point.
And I think that's what I wanted to say about CellProfiler features and
understanding and interpreting them.
Yeah.
No.
And, and definitely some of them will give you a picture in your head.
Like if I say my cell got has an area two times as big, you know, to your point
earlier, like some of the things definitely like the picture, like the info
measure, it's like, okay, the texture is kind of something about this, but I
don't really, but it should be enough to at least give you an idea of like what's
going on in the cell to try to give you idea of what's the next experiment to do.
Yes.
Yeah.
And certainly way more informative than, you know, feature 732, which might be the
name of the future you would get out of a deep learning model.
Right.
Like, um, so there is definitely always.
Some level of interpretability because you know what image, you know, what
compartment, um, and what category of measurement it is, even if it's, even if
it's not to get there is, is a big.
Awesome.
Well, thank you.
That was great.
And I love, I love your illustration.
Thank you.
Um, thanks for being here and thanks for joining.
Talk to you later.