Hey Beth, how's it going?
Hey Erin, it is so lovely to see you.
Oh my gosh, same thing right back at ya.
Yeah, so today on Ask Erin Dear Beth,
I thought it might be fun or help, I don't know, fun.
Yeah, fun, it's always fun.
Fun, absolutely fun.
To go through a list of conferences that we,
lots you, sometimes us and or the Cimini Lab,
have attended recently and or attend regularly just to say,
you know, hey, these are the vibes at this conference,
this is a thing we particularly like about it,
just to give folks out there an idea of like,
hey, these are some of the conferences you might want to come to
and maybe you'll run into us if you do.
Yeah, and I mean, there's a lot of good stuff out there,
depending on if you're into image analysis,
because you're into imaging or because you're into biology
or because you're into computer science,
like depending on where your flavor is,
like, there's actually, as we were getting this episode ready,
I was surprised just how many there are.
Yeah, yeah, and this is absolutely not even a comprehensive list
of the conferences that we go to.
This was, you know, things that we have gone to either a ton
or very recently, and so this is not exhaustive,
there is way more out there, but just sort of,
you know, nice broad strokes overview.
And feel free to drop in the comments
if you think there's an awesome thing
that we're missing and maybe we'll see you there.
Yes, absolutely.
So, I'm starting here with SBI2,
because that was where we most recently hung out, IRL,
even if we didn't get any video evidence of it.
We have lots of video evidence of both of us being there.
It's true, it's true.
You know, we got another podcast episode on that,
but just not the two of us in the same video frame
at the same time, which is silly,
we should do better next time.
Oh no, we were too having too much fun hanging out.
Yeah, yeah.
So, SBI2, Society of Biomolecular Imaging and Informatics.
Yeah, so basically, like, this is our whole lab,
our whole imaging platform, our sister lab,
Carpenter Singh lab, like, our, you know,
the entire, our whole office area disappears
for the duration of SBI2, everybody goes.
So, this is where you will, you know,
find the imaging platform very thoroughly represented
at this conference.
I think we were 10% of the attendees
at the 2025 SBI2 meeting?
Yeah, yeah, we took, you know,
grabbed a photo of Carpenter lab alums
and it was a solid chunk of the current conference.
So, SBI2, I think is cool and unique
in that it is a balance of both academic
and industry and pharma.
It seems like 50, 50, that's a total vibes-based number,
but, you know, a pretty good split
of getting both of those populations of researchers
together in the same room.
So, you get to hear both a lot of, you know,
more basic tech dev that happens more likely
in an academic setting as well as application
that is more likely to happen in a biotech pharma setting.
So, pretty cool bringing those groups together.
Yeah, it's, and it's on those sort of like spectrum
between like super focused on one area
to like a little bit for everything.
It's more on the super focused side
and it ends up being about sort of 250 to 300 people,
which is a meeting size that I personally like.
It's pretty focused.
You end up mostly talking about what do we do
with lots of images and figuring out sort of hidden
information from image data.
If that's something you like,
you will hear about it for three days.
That's not something you like.
It might not be the right conference for you
unless you wanna learn more.
Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
Though it does have, since it is a society meeting,
it does have very clearly an education focus
and recognizes that people are attending
that are coming from the sort of wet lab,
you know, wet lab and dry lab sides,
where people that have the expertise
in running the experiments in the wet lab
that wanting to understand more about the computational end,
as well as people who have computational expertise
but really wanna start diving into the biology,
you know, driving that.
So again, that's a super good point.
Yeah, yeah, a bit of a spread in that
and a nice way of bringing it all together.
So yeah, so that's SBI2.
Okay, ASCB, American Society for Cell Biology.
This is one that is probably like the least focused
conference that we regularly attend,
I would say, you know,
Cell Biology being a very large term.
And so you are likely to find a little bit of everything
related to Cell Biology at this conference.
Yeah, no, it's especially,
it feels like it's always a lot of cytoskeleton stuff.
It's one of the, definitely if you love cytoskeleton,
you will love ASCB, but it's a great place
to hear about things that you don't usually think about
and actually expose yourself to a different part
of cell biology than, you know, perhaps you would otherwise.
Yeah, yeah, that's a great point.
There's also usually, at least the last several years,
some good working groups on like,
how do we bring microscopy data people together
and things like that, which have been really cool.
Yeah, nice.
And I, you know, also have heard it as
because it is so big and so many people attend,
you know, smaller groups will use it as an excuse
for like, hey, let's pull together a pre-ASCB,
you know, educational day,
tacking it on as a great way for researchers
and collaborators all across the country
who are already planning on being at the same place
at the same time, will add on a day, you know,
to either end to be able to more directly focus
on a project.
So, you know, you may have a friend or collaborator
that this would be the perfect opportunity to excuse,
to like get you co-located,
that's the word I was going to say, co-localized, but, you know.
Oh, co-localized works, I'm all about it.
Yeah, all right.
SLAS, yeah, there's both society for lab,
lab automation and screening.
Thank you, yep, always stumble through that one.
So, SLAS is,
I think, does have some academics that come,
you know, we often come to SLAS meetings,
but it is, I think, much more heavily weighted
to biotech and pharma,
and very also focused on, well, automation, right,
being a part of it.
So, you know, as an academic, dry lab academic,
it's actually pretty fun to walk the conference floor
and look at all the robots that are for sale.
So many robots.
So many robots, you know, I'm never interacting with them
or seeing them in the lab,
because we just sit in front of our computer screens.
But, so if you're interested in,
you know, if that is already an area of your expertise
or you're interested in learning more about the automation,
then that is a cool opportunity.
They also are very focused on tech development.
So there's focus and awards for startups
that are driving technology
and for, you know, technological development,
which can be cool to sort of keep an eye on.
They also have interest groups.
So SLAS again being, you know, fairly broad,
but then have much more narrowly defined interest groups
that either meet at the main SLAS meeting,
we'll have an afternoon,
or even sometimes smaller subset conferences,
like we've been to SLAS AI,
that are then, you know, much smaller meetings
under the SLAS umbrella,
that can be a cool way to connect to people
with a much, you know, a much narrower interest.
And I will say, if you're early career person,
SLAS offers mentoring that you can sign up for.
Like you can, if you're going to the main meeting,
you can sign up to say, like,
here are some people who volunteered
to just like meet with people,
to sort of give them like a little bit
of career coaching or whatever.
And so I've done that in the past
and it's been really fun to get to meet with people
who are like, how did you get to be where you are?
And I think it's great, I wish more meetings did that.
So it's a very cool aspect of SLAS.
Nice, yeah, totally.
Okay, Cytodata.
Cytodata society also has a regular conference
and this is much more data focused
as one might infer from the name.
So there is, you know, let's see.
Yeah, we started with SBI2,
sort of the one end of SBI2,
that is the what do we do with large amounts of image data?
Like that is the focus of Cytodata
and really driving, you know,
working together and driving the data exploration
and of high content image experiments.
It also, they often have workshops
and they often have hackathons.
So if you like to, you know, meet up with new folks
and dive right into a project
and, you know, make some fast and dirty code,
then that can be a really fun opportunity to,
and the cool thing about it, you know,
the hackathon sort of environment,
like it doesn't, you bringing together people
of different skill sets and, you know,
different expertise and different levels
of proficiency with coding.
So you don't have to, you know,
you can participate and have a fun time
and even be on a winning team,
even if you don't feel like you are the most confident coder
because you are a biologist who learned to code
rather than being a trained software engineer
or data scientist.
And so that could be a fun thing about this conference.
Yeah.
And the connections I've made to folks
at Cytodata Hackathons, like people that now I'm like,
oh, if I need something in this area,
I will just totally email, you know,
a person that I met at one of these hackathons
because spending two days sort of solving a problem
together really, you know, helps you make friends.
Absolutely, absolutely.
Yeah, speaking of hackathons,
SciPy is another conference that we went to this year.
So this is about scientific Python,
scientific Python computing,
which again is much more broad,
you know, me, both niche and broad, you know,
narrow in that it is science focused and Python,
but also end up interacting with people
that are not bio-imaging at all,
people coming from engineering,
people coming from, you know,
I thought it was really cool I got to go
to some workshops on geospatial imaging,
which, you know, so a lot of the tools
and methods that they use are very helpful and relevant.
So it was really cool to learn about that,
but not something that I would generally be exposed to
all that much because I'm, you know,
focused on the bio part of the bio-imaging.
And there's also hackathons usually tied
to one end of SciPy.
Yeah, and I'll say as somebody who is a self-taught coder,
I felt kind of nervous about like going to the sprints
and everybody there is super lovely and welcoming.
And there are people there who are professional software
engineers who've been coding their whole lives,
but there are also people who are sort of area experts
in geospatial imaging or astronomy or biology
and who just, you know, like to code as part of their job.
And nobody I talked to was like,
oh, you don't have a software degree?
And they're like, oh, cool, nice to meet you.
So it was very friendly and welcoming.
Nice.
They also have a pun-off basically at the end of each day,
which I very much enjoyed.
Yeah, yeah, I did not make it to that.
And I do feel a little jealous
that that didn't fit into my schedule.
Yeah, ABRF is another one that we go to often.
It is, okay, Association for Biomolecular Research Facilities.
Oh, there we go.
I could have actually just read it right there.
I didn't have to pull that one out of my brain.
But there we go.
Resource facilities.
Yes, yeah.
Yeah, so ABRF, so Biomolecular Resource Facilities,
also known as core facilities,
which we are the imaging platform,
Broad Institute calls its core facilities platforms,
but, you know, we have the designation
of being a SSF specialized service facility.
So ABRF is a gathering of folks
that are involved in core facilities
across the United States.
And it is cool in that, you know,
if you are, it's way beyond bio-imaging,
there are all sorts of cool things happening
in core facilities.
So I get to go, you know, looking crazy talks
that I never would have thought about attending,
you know, like solving crimes using mass spectrometry.
Like, whoa, that was really fun.
But also they have a really strong emphasis on networking
and career development and sort of community
for the unique challenges that core facilities face
that are different than a sort of traditionally
grant funded lab.
So it's a pretty cool organization to get involved in
if you are a part of a core facility
or interested in being a part of a core facility
as a career path.
They also have smaller subset meetings, regional meetings,
again, like spread across the United States.
So you can, at those smaller meetings,
even connect more directly with people
that are geographically closer to you
and really get to make friends in community that way.
Yeah.
And since a lot of core facility people
are pretty isolated within their individual organizations,
you know, if a facility might only be one or two people,
it's a great way to sort of have people
who are just excited to connect to their peers.
Yeah, absolutely.
They also have some research groups.
So for example, the Light Microscopy Research Group
for ABRF has done some very cool studies
about like how well can people actually,
like can people tell if they're doing a good job
doing segmentation and things like that?
There's the, and they do these research studies
to actually try to figure out how well research goes
and can facilities do anything to make research better,
which I think is a great mandate.
Yeah, totally.
Okay, we went to the OME community meeting this year
where, okay, quick anecdote,
in the general, you know, arrive in the evening
general intro talk, it was, you know,
raise your hand if you came to this meeting for this reason
and raise your hand if you came for this reason.
And I sort of leaned over and whispered to Beth,
like, I don't know when to raise my hand.
I don't know why I'm here.
What am I doing here?
And then everybody, it's a small meeting.
So then everybody went to the local bar in the town.
This was at Woods Hole.
So, you know, wandered away into the bar that evening
to hang out with the other folks that were there.
And I didn't, there were a few people
that I had met before and interacted with,
but the majority of the people there I did not know.
So I was like, okay, time to sit down
and make some new friends.
So, plopped down and within five minutes,
I had a whole table full of people
that were just absolutely geeking out
about my personal recipe collection
and metadata curation of just my, you know,
my own hobby of curating and baking and cooking.
And so, you know, five minutes into the drinks,
I had like, I had found my people.
So whether, you know, they're like equally nerding out
about metadata.
I'm like, oh, okay.
So this is why I'm here because I love metadata
in every shape or form in my personal and professional life.
And so do these people.
They are just as nerdy about the same thing as me.
Like, okay, this is why I met OME.
Yep.
Yeah.
So OME is open microscopy environment groups of folks
that are interested in, particularly in standards.
Standards, I know, you know,
some of like not the sexiest topic like metadata and standards
which don't excite lots of people,
but if they do excite you, these are your people.
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
Anything else?
Also has a hackathon at the end
where people put together some cool projects.
We hashed out with somebody at last year's hackathon
and they like helped make part of something
for our bilayers project.
Cause they were just like, oh, that's a cool idea
that builds on standards.
And so again, super nice people for the people
who were there from work coders,
they're like, you can help with documentation.
But if you go to the meeting, if there's a hackathon,
definitely go to the hackathon too.
Yeah.
Yeah, absolutely.
Okay.
I2K, which is images to knowledge.
So, okay, you were the expert on this one Beth,
you should describe I2K.
Images to knowledge is a super interesting conference
that's never been the same twice.
And so in that sense, in 2018,
it was an in-person conference at EMBL.
2020, it was around the clock tutorial with on during COVID.
In 2022, it was a hybrid meeting.
In 2024, it was an in-person meeting.
And so it's just,
it's almost an experimental conference at this point.
It's kind of never been the same thing twice.
But what has been consistent for the past couple of years
is since that original 2020 around the clock hackathon,
every year except 2021 has had major aspects of I2K
that have been about doing tutorials.
So in the 2022 hybrid meeting,
the mornings and the afternoons were kept for tutorials.
And then since then,
we've been running these online events every year.
In odd years, they're the only event
and we call them halfway to I2K.
And in even years, they're the actual,
they're run alongside the actual event.
And what they are is we just say,
here's a tutorial with on.
We make a big Zoom platform,
the people who make the tools that you like.
And they don't have to be people who make the tools.
We have a lot of people who show up
and they're like, I really love QuPath
and I wanna teach other people how to do a thing in QuPath
that I just learned how to do if anybody wants to show up.
And it turns out people do wanna show up if you build it.
And so we, every year that we've done this,
we've had 30 plus different tutorials
on different aspects of image analysis.
You can register and attend for free
and go to as many of those as your schedule allows.
And it's just a great way for the community
to share what's exciting to do in image analysis.
I've just started planning a 2026 in-person meeting,
but there's hopefully gonna be some hybrid events too.
Awesome, yeah.
And there will be a special Ask Me Anything episode
of Ask Erin Dearbeth that we're gonna record
at halfway to ITK this year.
So please check that out
because that will have probably already been posted
by the time this episode goes up.
Yeah, yeah.
We will hopefully also do it again next year.
Yeah, love it.
Okay, last couple ones here to mention.
I pulled up Globias,
the Global Bioimage Analyst Society,
but there's a bunch of, maybe we have a lot.
I also pulled up here, BINA, there's NEUBIAS.
What other global ones do we have here?
Yeah, so BINA's not technically global,
but there is global bio-imaging that is sort of,
BINA is the sort of equivalent of global bio-imaging,
but these are all scientific societies
that have conferences.
And so if you wanna get together with folks
to talk about bio-imaging or bio-image analysis,
they have great meetings every year.
They're also great societies
that have a lot of working groups.
And so I'm in bio-imaging North America's
working group for image analysis.
And it's cool to get to meet friends
and talk to people who do that around the country.
And in Globias, I get to do that with people
who are around the world.
One of my favorite things about Globias
that isn't a conference, but that can sort of maybe be a thing
that sort of leads you to going to a Globias event some days.
We have an online database where you can say,
hi, I'm a bio-image analyst.
I wanna be contacted about opportunities to do stuff,
or I just want people to be able to find me on the internet
so that people who work near you,
who want help with bio-image analysis can find you.
Or if you wanna find somebody who does bio-image analysis,
you can use that tool to find somebody who's near you.
And Globias is still a pretty new society.
We only started it a couple of years ago,
but they just had their first sort of big
couple hundred person conference
and hopefully more conferences in years to come.
Yeah, and I think the neat thing about actually
lots of what I put up here is societies
that have conferences.
And so even beyond, for Globias and BINA,
being two of the examples I pulled up,
they have all sorts of professional enrichment
and opportunities for networking and connecting and learning
and super informative newsletters
that are all a way to get involved,
a way to learn more.
And then also they have conferences
where you can do a lot of that in person,
but definitely worth checking out
checking out what the society has to offer
even beyond the conference.
Yeah.
No, it's a great point.
Like newsletters can be a great way to just see,
like is the society like interested in things
that I'm interested in?
Many years I don't make it to ASCB
just because December's hard, but I have their newsletter
and so I can see what's ASCB up to.
And I definitely don't make it to all of these every year
because I need to sometimes get work done,
but it's great to keep up with those societies
and see the important work that they're doing.
Yeah, absolutely.
Well, thank you for talking through that list.
Again, this is not an exhaustive list
of the conferences and societies that we love and attend.
This was just, again, some of the most recent ones
that we have been actively involved with.
So if there are other similar societies
or conferences that you love, let us know,
drop it in the chat and maybe we could repeat this
in the future sometime with another chunk of ideas for folks.
All right.
That was so fun.
Thank you.
Thanks, bud.
Here we go.