Hello!
So wonderful to see you as always.
I agree!
So I thought we might talk about Cell Painting.
I know, I think we never talked about it.
But actually what I figured I would talk about is like we've talked a lot about Cell Painting
and what it is.
But a lot of people might realistically be thinking like, I don't know, like I have particular
biology I want to see.
This whole idea of Cell Painting is kind of weird.
And so what I thought I might talk about is what we know about the Cell Painting essay
and how you can modify it and therefore whether or not you can use it for data that includes
your own stuff.
Cool.
Yeah, I mean I think that's true.
It's like a question we get all the time of like, okay, can I, you know, fill in the
blank here?
Like, can I change it in this way?
Like great starting point, love the essay, but.
So now we're going to like fill in the information about the but part.
Or people might be like, well, I don't have the same microscope you have.
Like does that matter?
Like that's a totally reasonable, like you don't want to go buy a new microscope.
Absolutely.
I mean the whole point of this, one of the whole points of this essay when it was developed
is to make it as accessible to as many average microscopists as possible.
Cool.
So let me just quickly talk about and try to make a little separation between their
Cell Painting and Cell Painting means this particular set of dies.
It means Huxed, Concanavalan A, Mitotracker Red, Wheat Germaglutinin, Filoiden, and Cytophoreteen.
So like when we say Cell Painting, like we specifically mean this.
Whereas image based profiling is sort of like the broader approach.
Like can we measure things about cells and do like high dimensional clustering basically.
So how much of the magic in Cell Painting is the Cell Painting and how much of it is
the image based profiling.
So that was actually a thing that we thought was going to be really important to measure
when we did the whole jump which was a joint undertaking in morphological profiling but
where we did a big consortium where we had lots of companies doing this together.
We figured we should figure out and so we did a ton of experiments to talk about like
what aspects of this actually matter.
And one reason that you know it's important to sort of know like do we need all of these
dies is because we have like completely taken up the spectrum.
Like there's no part of the spectrum that is left.
Like most microscopes don't have good filter sets here but like we're totally covering
everything that so we can't add anything else.
So very often the question is do we need all of these dies?
Could I get rid of some so I could put something else in?
So we want to know like do we actually need all of those dies?
And so let me walk you through how to read this figure.
So at the top left is what if we only have size and shape measurements?
When we pretend we have no dies at all obviously you can't get cell size and shape from like
no dies but what we did is we measured all of the dies but then we computationally dropped
out the measurements of some of them.
And then as we go across on the top or on the sides we add more dies back in.
So we go from measurements of none of the dies just things like shape and neighbor features
to every single die here.
And what you'll probably notice is like there is a gradient in general sort of like as we
go from top left to bottom right like we get darker.
But also it's not actually that strict of a gradient like some combinations of features
sort of just look particularly good.
And also in general this scale bar goes from 49 which in this case is percent of compounds
we can sort of reliably retrieve to 57.
Like it's actually not a huge difference between having as many of the dies possible
and the best result possible and no particular features at all besides size and shape.
So and we did a whole lot of other things that are in the paper that's in the bottom
right there to sort of say like our different classes of features more important in size
and shape aren't especially important features but what it turns out is like none of these
features especially are important.
We can get rid of any of them and be totally fine and not be penalized like it's not that
we're only have good performance down here at the bottom right.
So you can take out any of our dies and put your own in.
These dies are not magical they're not special it really just seems like it's the total amount
but not actually like that these dies are beautiful and magical and special.
And can you are you going to say anything like I've always I think many people once they
start diving into this figure then get surprised right like why is it that the highest value
isn't is actually a subset of the stains like how is it better to have fewer what's going on there.
Yeah I wasn't going to talk about that but I can tell you and I can say we don't know for sure
but what we suspect is happening in those cases is just we're always balancing between like
are more features adding more biology or adding more noise and it might be that once you get beyond
sort of a certain amount of biology that's captured you actually just start confusing
the ability to separate these particular sets of compounds so this is 90 particular
compounds that cover 47 different sort of biological things so they certainly do not
cover everything in biology but we suspect that it starts becoming in some of these cases a like
signal to noise balance and that there's just so many things that could be different but
aren't actually important that the models start having a harder time figuring out what is the
real thing that matters. So that's our hypothesis we don't actually know for sure we don't think
any of these days are bad and as I'll sort of talk about in a little bit like even if this
dye was bad for this task it might be good for other tasks but yeah that's our hypothesis I wish
I could say for sure. Well and it's you know it's always really interesting again we sort of
looking carefully at there are many spots that hit the highest value of 57 and even more that are
hitting 56 right which again isn't all that far away from the starting point of 49 but if you were
to filter it to just things hitting the best you know performing the best the combinations of 56
or 57 it's actually sort of very non-consistent combinations right yeah like it's not that so
again it's not that AGP, mito, and bright field high right are the exact perfect combination and
everything. I think you know again as you're saying that's why part of why our guess is it's
some but not too you know like capture a bunch but not too much or sort of hand waving. Yeah
but as long as the biology is diverse like none of these particular stains are like the stain
that when we get rid of it like everything is different. Absolutely absolutely which you know
again to your major point here the major the major thing to take away from this is yeah get rid of
whatever in here get rid of several whatever's if you have a specific thing you want to put in
instead do that. Yeah and so we actually found a lot of things that didn't matter when we when the
more of these kinds of experiments we did during jump. So what we found doesn't matter include
things like what magnification you take the images at after you're talking about if you're
taking them at 10x or 20x or 40x it doesn't really matter. Whether you're using a higher exposure
time or a lower exposure time and these are just in all of these cases like two different measurements
of like being able to match profiles with each other like doesn't particularly matter.
If you're doing this on whitefield or if you're doing this on confocal doesn't especially matter.
If you're doing this in two different cancer cell lines at a couple of different densities
it does not especially matter.
If you're doing this with your binning turned on or turned off it doesn't particularly matter.
Who you bought your dies from does not really particularly matter.
Nothing really actually matters. This was my proposed but internally rejected
graphical abstract for this paper. But I do just want to say before I say one last thing like
what do I mean by doesn't matter. When I say that these things don't matter I mean four tasks like
this where what we're saying is what fraction of compounds can we sort of match up with themselves.
So for this clustering task which is what image based profiling is for
those sorts of things don't matter. But every other measurement that we take in image based
profile like we've talked before about that we can take thousands of measurements
is still a microscopy measurement is still a biological measurement.
And if ultimately you care about your clustering but also why your things are clustering the way
you are and we've talked in the past about trying to make Cell Painting interpretable and trying
to figure out what features matter. If you want to be able to trust the features mattering
of course doing things like making sure you're working at a magnification where you can see
the things you care about matters that your exposure time is not completely saturating
your objects or you know completely you know unable to see them of course it matters.
So don't take from this please that what Beth is saying is like you can do bad microscopy
and do Cell Painting. I'm not saying that like I'm saying within reasonable microscopy choices
and the good thing is if you've done much microscopy you can tell if your brightness is in a good
regime if it seems like your images are clean or not so clean they don't have to be perfect.
We've done other episodes about like things you can do to clean up or find things that are out of
focus or stuff like that like we're not saying your experiment has to be perfect but as long as
your experiment is reasonable you can get to do this image based profiling assay and think about it
as like a free bonus assay. So there's really no reason to not if you're taking images and you have
a spare part of the spectrum Cell Painting dyes come in all parts of the spectrum you might as well
just throw in a couple more dyes that you carefully check don't perturb you know the biology you want
to make sure that you measure but measure the biology that you make sure you want to measure
and then you can add in image based profiling and get all this information about clustering and get
these potentially interesting patterns in the extra dyes that you didn't know about for almost
free because these dyes are really cheap and the analysis approach is free. So don't worry that if
you want to try image based profiling but you're not sure you have the right cell type or the right
microscope or you know you're not sure exactly if you can afford one of the fancy reagent kits and
you're just like well can I use stuff I already have the magic is in the approach the magic is not
in you buying a particular die kit or following our exact protocol if you do generally good microscopy
you can do image based profiling too and you might get cool results that you might not have
gotten if you hadn't thought to do this. I love it and and in the Cell Painting gallery we have
many example data sets of people that have done just that you know adapted the classic Cell Painting
assay a little bit to add on specific biology that they wanted to capture in their screen along with
the basic morphological panel. So we have you know lipositic a lipositic derivation to specifically
look at fat distribution we have neuro painting we have ones that you once that swapped out
mitotracker for lysotracker yeah yeah you know or the variant painting ones where they wanted to
look for where individual proteins were so they have a flagged tagged antibody as one of the channels
but the rest are like Cell Painting channels. Yeah lots of lots of cool examples of people
doing exact you know doing exactly what you just set up showing you know swapping enough around
to make sure they captured their specific biological question but then also add it on top
like okay since I'm looking for my question let's fill up the rest of the space then
with things that I can then also do the morphological profiling. Yeah and so it's worth
it's not that much more money in terms of dyes in fact it might be nothing because a lot of
these are dyes you already have and you might learn something extra and so we would say don't be
scared try it out you know optimize for your biology but then maybe get some extra cool dyes in there too.
I love it and it's the most like the take home here is like the combination of the most nihilistic
and yet optimistic like yeah like nothing matters but isn't that exciting you know.
Nothing matters which means no matter sort of what the rest of your experiment needs to look like
probably Cell Painting will work for you too so nothing matters is actually a message of hope.
Yeah I love it. Well thanks for letting me talk about you know non-canonical Cell Painting but
all image based profiling is great no matter what dyes you use. I love it thanks Beth. Yeah thank you.