Hey Beth!
Hey Erin!
How's it going?
It's good.
Welcome to another episode of Ask Erin and Dear Beth.
Here we go.
What do we got?
We got today, we're going to look at binucleation and what makes it hard to look at in CellProfiler
and therefore what can we do to make it a little bit better in CellProfiler?
Awesome sauce.
Yeah, definitely something that is not something you would necessarily expect to be hard but
because of some weird things about how what CellProfiler makes in terms of assumptions
can be unexpectedly a challenge.
All right, well let's dive right in.
What is CellProfiler expecting and how do we hack CellProfiler?
I mean we hack CellProfiler in lots of ways.
I know, I know.
That is probably much too big of a question for us but like how are we going to specifically
hack CellProfiler in this exact circumstance to help us deal with these multi-nucleate
cells?
Yeah.
So CellProfiler sort of has the assumption under the hood that cells and nuclei belong
together.
And the reason it has that assumption is generally because when you're looking at cells, cells
might be hard to figure out where one ends and the next one begins especially if they
sort of get up on each other and they're touching each other and you know here we have some
cells that are actually pretty nicely behaved but still we zoom in sort of right in this
particularly crowded region.
I'm not sure I could say the exact pixel where this cell you know stops and this cell starts.
And you're going to run into that situation a lot with cells.
Cell culture you know those are somewhat contact inhibited most of the time but they definitely
do like to sort of get pretty close to each other.
Yeah and again that's also a thing that's very dependent on cell type.
But most of the time what we try to do when you're working with images of cells like this
is get cells that behave nicely and don't grow on top of each other.
So these are actually like pretty nicely behaved cells.
You know there are definitely cell lines that are even much harder to parse than this where
they like to start growing on top of each other and you know you might be in like here
there probably is a single pixel that is the transition point from one cell to the other
that we just don't you know can't tell enough from the image ourselves to figure out what
that is.
And we're not even addressing the regime where there actually isn't a single pixel because
cells are growing on top of each other.
Like that's not even what we're talking about in this instance.
Like these are nicely behaved cells for image analysis like this.
Yeah exactly.
On the other hand nuclei tend to be much nicer and much better behaved.
So let's also adjust the contrast on these guys.
And I'm doing this just by control clicking.
And you can see we've got a couple cases where things are touching but overall the number
of cases where we wouldn't be sure exactly which pixel goes with exactly which nucleus
are a lot less and in general things are much more well defined.
So when you can get away with it, Subprofiler recommends just sort of by its existing structure
that you start by identifying nuclei and you build the cells around them.
So here's what that looks like in practice.
In our object processing, we always start with identify primary objects and what primary
objects means in this case is we're building an object based on only one piece of information
the image.
We're not using any other information.
Become more clear in a second when we look at identify secondary objects and we have a
second piece of information.
If I go into test mode and I just leave the default settings on for now, this is probably
not going to work for, that actually worked pretty well.
Level for default settings.
Yeah, it's almost like we tuned those for a reason.
These aren't perfect but they're not terrible.
One of the things I'm specifically looking for here is I'm tuning things are these diameter
settings and it says that in general things are ranging between at the 10th percentile
16.5 pixels across at the 90th, 26.5.
And so the reason I'm looking at that is in general it looks like the right things are
being identified.
They're just being broken down wrong.
And the easiest way to change that, if Subprofiler wasn't picking up on what is a nucleus and
what isn't, I would need to change my thresholding settings.
But if all I need to do is change how the nuclear stuff is broken down into discrete
nuclei, sometimes I don't even have to do anything away from the default settings.
I can just adjust the object size.
Lovely.
There we go.
So pretty.
Now it's not doing a great job here when the objects are touching so maybe I'll try
and go down a little bit further and see if I can see if I can split the difference between
10 and 15.
Otherwise we'll take a quick look at the advanced settings.
And hey look, 15 did the trick.
Magical.
Wow.
Yeah.
So now we have all of our objects, even this one which looks like it is actually two different
things.
They're just very similar in the color scheme.
This one says it's object 52 and that one's object 53.
Awesome.
Nice.
But one thing to note here is that by changing here in our easy mode, the simple mode, changing
the typical diameter, there are things happening under the hood that default assumption cell
profiler is making to help segment those apart.
We could go to advanced settings and find two and lots of those things on our own.
But just...
We don't have to.
Here, just changing that diameter, CellProfiler knows enough to figure out those objects.
Great.
So now that we have our nuclei and they're lovely and beautiful, we can add a second
object.
We can say, hey CellProfiler, use the cytoskeleton image and the nuclei and build cells around
the nuclei.
And again, when you have a mononucleot image, that works.
And hey look, this is beautiful.
We now get things that look like cells.
They're a little on the sort of underside, so we might change our thresholding method
to try to pick up a few more things.
But again, the goal here is not to have things perfect.
The goal here is just to get some things that are plausible cells.
Okay, that didn't do a whole heck of a lot.
I could tune it more.
I don't really need to.
You get the idea.
We had nuclei, we made them into cells.
Great.
I'm going to actually just change the default scaling here as we're looking at stuff, which
I can find in these settings and MAC, it's called preferences.
And that's just going to make it so that things generally look prettier and it's a little
easier to follow along with what we're doing here.
How does that now look?
That looks worse.
All right.
So.
80 was okay.
We'll go with 99, just because that seems like a fun number.
One thing to point out, this isn't doing anything about changing the underlying data.
This is just how it's being shown to us here as we're looking at these.
We can now see the cell boundaries a little bit more easily and just in general get a
better sense of what's going on.
Yes.
This is just a display visualization.
And yes, now we can see these much more easily too.
Great.
And here, sorry.
Just want to also point out that depending on your task, you may be spending more time
or less time in your ID secondary to get perfectly the very edges of your cells.
Here we're just not spending the time fine tuning because our task right now is just
to explain to you about multi-nucleate cells.
So we just need to find edges that sort of make enough sense that we can go through this
demonstration.
If you were to be doing quantitative image analysis on the cell objects, perhaps you
would be iterating more at this point.
For sure.
Now let's get a sense of what this is going to look like in the case of multi-nucleation.
So I'm going to tell CellProfiler to let me pick an image set.
Now I'm going to go down to the ones from our positive control image and get some cells
from there.
Okay.
Whoa, that's bad.
So CellProfiler has, in some cases, it has messed up and sort of put two nuclei into
one.
In some cases, the nuclei are so big, there are so many of them that this has now turned
pink, which means it says this thing is too big.
I think it's all one thing.
And I think it's too big of a thing.
It's a thing that's bigger than what you told me you want.
I'm throwing it away.
And in some cases, it's doing kind of the right thing, though those cases are pretty
rare, to be honest.
So here we have what I would count as five, and we have one, one, and three.
So not great.
But potentially even more not great is when we look at our cell calling.
So the fact that these, that we sometimes have cases where two, what is clearly two
nuclei have been stuck into one actually helps us get the right cell mask because CellProfiler
is still assuming that nuclei and cells are one to one.
But in this case, where it actually did do a good job of splitting some nuclei off, now
we're in a terrible position in that this cell is now broken into chunks, which is definitely
not what we wanted.
Yes.
That does not, you know, that does not look like the cells we want.
So I think cell chunks anytime you're just like not a descriptor that we generally want
in our biology.
So I really have kind of three choices here.
One of them is I can try to force CellProfiler to make all of the nuclei that touch be one
thing.
So all of these nuclei would be one thing.
This cell wouldn't get broken up.
But in cases like this big chunk here where there are multiple nuclei that we're touching
that are actually part of multiple different cells, those things are now going to be stuck
together.
I'm also not going to be able to count for multi-nucleation because multi-nucleation,
the nuclei are being detected sort of intentionally and correctly.
But if cell boundaries are important, that might be the best thing to do.
Yeah.
So one thing to really consider at the beginning of building your pipeline is what is your
output that you're looking for?
What is your downstream task?
What are you trying to measure?
In this situation, maybe you don't actually care about any measurements of the nuclei.
Maybe what you're really concerned about is something happening in the cell.
So all you really need is the cell boundaries.
And then we don't actually care to identify the individual nuclei parts.
But maybe that's actually really important if your downstream task is to measure the
number of nuclei or something related to a measurement in the nuclei themselves.
And so strategy of any workflow is definitely very dependent on the output that you want.
Absolutely.
Which is why we want, even though we are professional bio-image analysts, we're good
at doing bio-image analysis.
We want people who are just biologists who want to answer bio-image analysis questions
to understand how to do it.
Because you understand ultimately if it's more important to know more about the cells
or more about the nuclei.
And so you are the best person to design your image analysis workflow.
Absolutely.
We're always happy to help.
But your input is not optional.
It is essential to us designing the right workflow, even if we are the ones designing
it.
So I said that was one option.
The second option is to, instead of trying to force CellProfiler further into the direction
of sort of stick stuff together, we can try to force CellProfiler more into the direction
of split stuff apart.
It's going to get our nuclei correct.
But it's going to mean that if we keep using this ID primary and ID secondary, that we
end up with cell chunks.
Which again, maybe is fine.
Because if what you want to say is are the multinucleate cells different phenotypically
than the other ones, they sure are.
They sure are different if this cell is only a piece of a cell as opposed to a whole cell.
So if what you care about is just detecting phenotypic difference, that might be the right
way to go is to just have cell chunks.
The other third option is to abandon this ID primary, ID secondary sort of workflow entirely
and just use completely separate identifications for our nuclei and our cells.
Then we can try to get the best nuclear segmentation we can.
We can try to get the best cell segmentation we can.
But if the cells are really clumpy, that might not be very good cell segmentation.
There's a reason we do this in the first place.
And it's that cell segmentation is typically kind of hard.
In the interest of what we really hope you get here more are the concepts.
The cells segmentation here actually, now that you understand how it works, doesn't really
matter.
If I wanted to force the nuclei that are all touching to be all the same object, that's
one very easy setting and identify primary objects.
Let's just method to distinguish clumped objects.
None.
Do not distinguish clumped objects.
If nuclei are touching, just call them all the same thing.
I'm now going to have to adjust my sizing amounts because now these really big things
are being told that they're too big and CellProfiler doesn't want to count them anymore.
But I could do that.
That would be one way to go.
That's so easy.
Good thing to notice here.
We don't actually think that there are nuclei that are 500 pixels in diameter.
That was just throw out a large number because we have filter the objects outside of the
diameter range.
If we just pick a really large number, then we don't have to worry about it using it to
filter.
But because we have this in advanced settings mode especially, it's not using that to approximate
anything else or affect anything else.
The other things we could do are a little bit harder to walk through in a short thing.
We will have a future episode.
Erin remind me to have a future episode on declumping when things are really crowded.
But we can certainly do things that would push CellProfiler towards forcing the nuclei
to be smaller and more separate.
There's preprocessing tricks we could go to push this even further.
We've now at least gone further than we were before and we have smaller nuclear chunks.
This one is a little bit better.
But this is hard.
Especially if we zoom in on some of these ones that aren't doing a good job.
I think there are four nuclei here.
One, two, three, four.
But even I'm not totally sure.
One could be three.
Maybe it's one horizontal.
I don't know.
That's tricky.
I think that's a ridge.
I think there's four.
It's hard to say.
But if you are thinking of...
Sorry.
I was just going to say, I think that's a reminder about basic principles of image analysis.
Here, we are two expert biologists and we are having a very hard time saying where is
the line on this nucleus?
The computer can only do what we tell it to do.
When we get into this computational regime of thinking, it still relies on...
You still rely on expert biologist input to this task.
It will only do what we tell it.
We need to be able to tell it, to tune it to the regime that we think matches biology
best.
Sometimes, you can only get what you can get out of the image.
Maybe it's just not possible to tell.
You can't do better because you have no ground truth or expert biologist vision to compare
it to.
If we really cared, we could probably do things like look at the other channels and try to
get a sense.
I was saying before that I thought this clump was five and then when I looked at the cytoskeleton,
I thought it was six.
There are things we could try to do.
For now, I think we shouldn't because this is the case where we really want to turn to
deep learning.
We don't always want to turn to deep learning for everything because deep learning, it's
harder to understand when it will fail.
There are really good deep learning models for segmentation now.
Our very, very favorite is a tool called Cellpose.
If you haven't tried Cellpose yet, you absolutely should.
It is wonderful made by the folks at Janalia.
Great free open source tool.
Here we're running it in CellProfiler using a tool called Docker, which allows it to run
in its own little container, which means I didn't have to do any difficult installation
to install Cellpose on my machine instead of having to go to my terminal and try and
do things, which many of us do not want to do anything in our terminal.
I opened up the Docker desktop program and I searched for Cellpose and then I looked
for the one that was said CellProfiler RunCellpose.
That was all I did.
Then I added the RunCellpose, CellProfiler plugin.
You can check out, I believe it's Weisbart et al., 2023 to learn more about CellProfiler plugins
and how to use those.
Maybe that's a good future episode idea there too.
Maybe we should go deep dive into the plug-ins ecosystem.
Another one to add to the list.
Here I'm telling CellProfiler that I'm going to be using Cellpose with Docker, which means
I need Docker open and all, which I have.
I wanted to detect nuclei and I'm going to tell it that I think my nuclei are about 15
pixels across because that worked pretty well before.
I'm not going to try and tune any of the other parameters right now.
There's lots of other parameters in Cellpose like any CellProfiler module.
There are help functions next to each one of these things and you can get the help about
what is going on with each parameter by checking the help.
Always the most important button in CellProfiler.
Why are you unhappy?
I think you aren't unhappy.
I think you're just pretending.
I think it's just pretending.
I think that's ...
Yeah.
An outstanding issue that is not affecting functionality at the moment, but affecting what it's ...
It's a little cranky, but it does actually work.
Yeah.
Cellpose is really good at figuring out when stuff is clumped how to actually split it apart.
Often when we are doing multi-nucleation workflows these days and by these days, I mean in the
past five years since Cellpose was first proposed, that is the case where we don't
try to do things with classical CellProfiler anymore, but we actually leverage these deep
learning modules because the fact that they're a little harder to install and that they're
a little bit harder to predict when they will fail is outweighed by the fact that they just
work better at these tasks.
We're not never deep learning people and we're not always deep learning people.
You're deep learning when you weigh the factors and the factors balance.
This is unfortunately pretty slow in Docker in CellProfiler four.
When we put out CellProfiler five, this will be much faster, at least the second time.
On the first time, it's always going to be a tiny bit slow because it has to actually
make a whole system for running Cellpose.
The downside of installing really quickly is that it is not actually going to run super
quickly.
Okay, there we go.
As soon as I navigated away, it finished.
Here that input image looks terrible because of the normalization stuff.
Let's just put that back to normalized.
You can see with literally zero parameter tuning other than saying what is the approximate
size of the objects, Cellpose has done a way better job than our initial things did
and certainly better than I think even if Erin and I spent a bunch of time doing it,
I think Cellpose would probably do better in the long run.
This super big chunk that we were never able to split apart, it hasn't perfectly split
apart.
I still think there's a couple things that are stuck together, but it is way, way better
and there's more stuff we could do to tune things.
If you have a multi-nucleation workflow and things are super clumpy and it's really important
for you to be able to detect the bi-nucleation, using Cellpose and using Cellpose even sometimes
twice, once to be able to identify the nuclei and once to be able to identify the cells
is actually the way to go because when things are likely to be clumpy and weird looking,
then Cellpose is probably going to do the better job.
Again, this will probably take about a minute to run.
What are the things you just tuned in this module, Beth, as you were chatting?
Yeah, that's a great question.
I tuned which Cellpose model to run.
I changed it from nuclei before to cytohere, which is their cytoskeleton model.
Because we now want to find the cells, I switched which image to use.
I told it to use the cytoskeleton image instead of the DNA image.
Cellpose has actually been trained to assume that cells have nuclei.
I might be tuned to have cells one nuclei, so that might actually hurt.
What I just did might actually make it worse by turning the supply nuclei image as well
on or maybe not.
I'm not actually sure.
That's the sort of question where you could try and read the documentation or you could
just look and see what happens.
I always like to look and see what happens.
Nothing against documentation.
I read and write lots of documentation, but sometimes you just want to see in this exact
circumstance what's going to happen.
With deep learning, it can be really hard to tell, which is why we don't always go to
deep learning first.
But I did tell it that it could have a nuclear image as well.
I also changed the expected diameter.
We said nuclei were about 15 pixels across.
I said, let cells be about 25 pixels across.
That was vibes-based.
I think Cellpose is normalizing the image itself.
It hasn't detected our super big cell because it's super big and it has actually broken
things to where the nuclei are.
I'm going to try running this one more time and I'm going to not give it the nuclear image.
We're going to see if it'll do a better job.
I think it's still not going to pick up this cell because the cell is just so big.
There's stuff we could play with, but that's another episode.
Let's see if we don't give a nuclear image if some of these things, it gets a little
better, like this cluster.
When we give it the cell diameter, do you think there'd be a situation where bumping
up the cell diameter in this setting?
A bit?
Because I think 25 seems to be on the smaller end of things.
Maybe that will also help.
We're going to be using the same thing here.
In our identify secondary module, identify primary and identify secondary, when we're
putting the object diameters, in those examples, we were using them as hard cutoffs saying,
don't give me an object that is outside of this range that we put here.
In Cellpose, this RunCellpose module, this is different.
This isn't a hard cutoff for object diameter.
There is also a hard cutoff.
It's this minimum size parameter.
But yes, the expected object parameter isn't.
It's a guiding fact.
We want to be careful about setting that too big, though, because we want to make sure
that this pipeline also works for the ones where we still have little individual cells.
We don't want to go crazy.
We don't want to make it too big.
But yes, we can see if those changes help.
That's a good principle for when you are building a pipeline.
You always want to make sure that you are testing it on.
If you have positive and negative controls, great.
Make sure you're testing it on both of those.
As Beth mentioned, any parameter that we're setting up here to work on these cells, we
need to make sure it's also going to work on our negative control population, where
the cells look a lot different.
Having a broad enough test during your pipeline development is essential.
It doesn't look like actually those changes made a whole lot of difference, which is not
the answer I would have expected.
But again, deep learning can be a little bit hard to predict when things go well and when
they don't.
There's a lot of other cell post parameters we could test and we could tune.
There's a lot of other CellProfiler ones we could.
What we really wanted to do here is illustrate to you what things you might try in terms
of thinking through the problem.
Do we want to prioritize nuclear correct?
Do we want to prioritize cell boundary correct?
Or do we want to go to this deep learning situation, which is a little harder to predict,
but may work better?
All of those are valid pathways, potentially depending on the biology you want to measure.
All of those could then be further tuned to get the exact best answer for your data.
I don't think the tuning will teach you as much as the principles, because the tuning
will be specific to the data you have.
Absolutely.
Any closing thoughts, Erin?
No, no.
I mean, I think this is, you know, it's a fun challenge.
And again, I think an interesting thought exercise in remembering that like there are
many very valid approaches that will give you very different measurements in the end.
And so paying attention to what is my task and what do I need to, you know, what am I
prioritizing in accuracy is definitely something to keep in mind that has, I mean, I think
for any workflow, but it has a major impact on this particular example.
Let's go sticking out and sticking around and hanging out with us.
It was great to see you and hope to see you next time.
Bye.