Hello Beth!
Erin, hi!
How are you?
Peachy keen, how are you my dear?
Good, so lovely to see you.
And you as well.
Yeah, I have been worried about something though.
We told people that we were going to be doing a little bit of a tour
and we were going to be doing a little bit of a tour
and we were worried about something though.
We told people that we had a rule
and we didn't tell them why we had a rule.
We just told them they had to follow us and listen to us
and like that never feels good.
I mean, sometimes it feels good to just be like,
hey follow my rules, but I see what you're saying.
Specifically a couple episodes ago we said,
if you're doing ilastik, use the small brush size
and just do it.
We're not going to explain to you why in this video, just do it.
Figured probably be good to actually talk about why.
Sounds great. Let's dig in.
Alright, I have a simulator for us today.
Ooh.
Alright.
So today let's not actually look at ilastik or talk about ilastik.
Let's talk about sort of the principles that underlie ilastik.
So ilastik, at least in its sort of normal mode,
relies on a form of machine learning called a random forest.
And I'll explain exactly what that means in a second.
Essentially a random forest is what if we make a bunch of decision trees
and then we let the decision trees sort of make the decision forest.
We have a whole bunch of trees, so it's a forest.
And the random part of random forest means that what it does
is actually subsamples the data
and then makes decision trees with different parts of the data.
Hmm. Okay.
So I have this cool notebook that is based on a plotting library
that actually allows you to draw in some data.
And so I'm going to actually draw in some data now
that we can use to sort of make two classes and see how random forest works.
I like this.
Draw your own data.
Like easiest way to a figure, right?
Use your powers for good.
Alright, so here I have two different classes.
I can actually have up to four classes here,
but I have my blue points and I have my green points.
And I've drawn in some data and I have about 50 to 60 of each.
And my random forest says that it can separate those with 100% accuracy,
which makes sense because, you know, these are actually really different.
Right now my random forest is learning X position, Y position,
and then the size, which is a pretend number that we can sort of assign.
And right now the sizes are all assigned as the same.
So the sizes are not being really used by my random forest classifier.
It's making all its decisions based on X and Y,
because the X is different and the Y is different.
So that makes a lot of sense.
And so what we can do is we can actually look at what our random forest is.
So our random forest is actually 100 different decision trees.
If I want, I can pull up any decision tree I want.
I can pull up decision tree 30.
And I can see what that looks like.
And in that one, it says if the Y value is less than a certain number,
call it class two, otherwise call it class one.
And we can look at just the first nine and we can see that some of them start with X,
some of them start with Y, some of them have one level,
some of them have a couple of levels.
But essentially what this does is it then goes through for every data point.
And for it goes, puts it through all 100 trees and then says, okay,
in 80 of these trees, it says it's class one and in 20, it says it's class two.
The wisdom of the crowd must be right.
And so therefore we should call this class one.
So it's not using any single tree to make a decision.
It's saying like, let's, yeah, let's look at all of these trees.
So in your example, right, like the Y value alone gives us potentially lots of the information we need.
But if we, you know, if we're looking at those points, we need both X and Y values to be able to separate them.
So the decision tree, each individual decision tree contains not sufficient information.
It's the collection of the trees.
That's the forest that has like all of the information that we would need to separate.
No, I mean, so what you just said is a really good point.
We don't in theory in this example need the X or the Y or and the Y because it could be either the X or the Y because I made a point to sort of make these on a diagonal.
If I didn't, if say I drew this so that now it's only the X or the Y and the Y, like what if I do this?
And I'm going to, for reasons that I sort of explained later, just add a few more blue points here too.
So now we do need the X and the Y.
And it still says like X and Y are both important.
It's a little more weighted towards X now because we have a bunch of things over here.
But you can see now our trees have gotten a lot more complicated.
Because it really does need the X and the Y both in order to sort of figure out is this related to, is this part, is this a green dot or is this a blue dot?
Okay, so each individual tree, like in the first instance, each individual tree, well, I guess on this one too, it's the same principle, is actually saying like this tree, I think I can distinguish between the populations using just the rules in my tree.
But we have our level of confidence, not, you know, we're making our overall rules or our overall cluster designations based on consensus between each of those different versions.
Yes, exactly. And so each tree, and let me go down to a single tree now.
So we now have a little under 600 total data points.
So the random part comes in where each of the trees actually doesn't have the whole information.
So here, like, here's a random tree, it has 186, so it has about 30% of the information.
And so that's part of how we get the trees to all look different is you say, each one only has a sub sample of the information.
And so, otherwise, you would just get the same tree 100 times and it wouldn't actually be valuable.
But by saying, all right, we're going to sub sample the data, then we can, we can get different trees each time and we can hopefully get more robustness in our overall classifier by because we're going to get more robustness.
And so we can get more robustness in our overall classifier by because we're calling on sort of the wisdom of crowds here.
So how does this actually relate to ilastik and what the heck does this have to do with a pixel brush.
I swear, I swear it connects.
All right. So, all of that is how random forest work what are nurses have to do with ilastik why are we talking about a one pixel brush like what on earth is the relevance of how does a random forest work.
And so, first because ilastik is using a random forest under the hood. And we have our if we think about our annotations here.
We can think of them just like the pixel annotations that we make in ilastik in that each one each pixel annotation we make has a certain pieces of information, you know, x, y and size, for example, here but in ilastik it's like different textures
And it matters because there's some principles about how machine learning works that are sort of important to think about.
Here's one of them.
So, we can't control other than by turning some features on or off entirely what the machine learning algorithm uses in order to make its decisions.
It just makes the best decisions that can.
So, right. So I have my x and y but they're done in a way that are a little bit confusing that the have we have our trees are having to get pretty big in order for us to figure it out.
What happens if I take a different variable, like say size, and I make size super different between one of our two classes.
So, if I do this, our decision trees which before we're really using size at all because size was the same are now 50% based on size.
And so, and if we look at the actual trees.
It's not that size is always necessarily the first one, but that if we ask it for feature importance sizes rated as by far the most important feature.
So if what I want to learn as x y position and size is different.
Tough, tough nuggets.
The model is going to learn what the model wants to learn the model is going to say what is the easiest way for me to get this machine learning models whether they're deep learning or non deep learning will always.
cheat in that sense they will always just try to get the best answer they can.
And so, if what ilastik learns is that it should only learn things that are in sort of one image versus another image because it's way easier for it to learn that that's what it will do.
The other thing has to do with sampling. So right now I have a couple hundred points each for sort of my blue and green.
What happens if I try to sort of I'm going to add some red points they're going to be different color than the green here but they're going to belong to the same classes green.
So the model should treat these as if they were green dots, but they're different color for visualization point.
If I'm going to leave the size the same so that the size is a bad distinguisher but I'm going to put the red dots in the same place that the green dots are.
In theory that should make the model try to care more less about size and more about x y position again, because you know I'm telling it no you have this other class of things too.
So let's see what happens when I do that.
So, it has now said it's now still saying that it's 43.7% based on size.
Our trees now get super big and can eventually with enough depth figure out the difference between C and D, but they're not actually focusing on the thing that we think that we care about.
We haven't actually trained most of our model is still all about size.
And that's because only 10% of the things here are actually based on D. So I have 30 dots of D and 300 dots of C. So some of our trees only have a couple of red points total.
So this comes into maybe is like this fit in with the idea of them cheating right like it's ignore the red dots.
And they're fine because if there's only a couple then they still perform well on the other color than like cares about those couple of red dots.
Exactly. That's exact. And but because it's easy to get almost always the right answer, you know, by just ignoring a really small class.
So let me do an even more extreme example now instead of putting the dots here, I'm going to put the dots on top of the blue where they shouldn't be.
And if I only draw a few dots there I have 400 dots of green and only 10 dots of red.
It doesn't try to learn this at all. It just says nope. Okay, I have 0% accuracy on red. And that's fine.
Machine learning model goes.
Yeah. And now I have 10% as many. Still still 0% accurate.
I got up to 6% accurate now with like 75 versus 400 but you can see, as long as there is mathematically more points that look like this than points that look like that.
The model is not really giving a crap about these points. It's getting 100% accurate here. Apparently that was a little slow to upload now it's up to 15% before it had been about seven but you still it is definitely 100 versus 15.
It doesn't care about these points as as managers cares about these points.
And that is the thing about the one pixel brush. If you on your first image color in a whole bunch of stuff with a big brush.
If you now want to go to another image and say actually, you know, nuclei look like this and image one but image two has a different noise model or just a little brighter or a little dimmer.
And you start putting annotations if you don't put near as many annotations as you did for the first one.
Your modeling gonna care your model doesn't need to learn to care.
Because it can still be really accurate by ignoring your second image and only caring about your first image.
Plastic is really good does a lot of things to try to avoid this and you can see that even here we have like five or six times as many as much as see and it is now at least trying to learn the red points but it's still doing a pretty crap job at it.
So if you use a big brush, you now have to use a big brush all the time. If you annotate a lot of points you have to annotate a lot of points all the time.
This happens when you have like a rare pixel class where there's only 20 pixels of that thing in your whole image like maybe you'd want like a nuclear Ram or something else is like just a very small number of pixels.
If you have 400 pixels in one image and 20 in the other, you can't ever make the model care about 20 equally with 400 you just can't do models are going to learn whatever the heck they want to learn.
And so the only way to make your model care equally about all of the images you tell it about and all the things you tell it about is by telling them about it equally.
And so that could be using a huge brush if everything you want to find is big in all of your images and you don't mind spending a lot of time drawing.
You can also just annotate 10 individual pixels in each of a few images and be done faster and still preserve your ability to deal with rare cases because you haven't done this thing where you have 400 examples that look like this and only 70 examples that look like that.
I love it so our you know our rule isn't just to get people to be lazy because we love it when people are lazy.
You know, we want work to be as lazy as possible. But like you've clearly shown us here it's not just about being lazy. It's actually what's needed to get out the result you need at the end.
Yeah, so you get a better result and faster. I mean, why would you not want to do that when it's like well it could be worse and slower or better and faster.
That does seem like a pretty easy decision tree there.
Yeah.
I see what you did there.
And of course, I want to make the caveat of here, my decision trees are based on three total things x y and size and they're very simple things and this is often kind of what the case is when we're doing fluorescence.
When you start getting into very complicated things like EM, which is what ilastik is originally designed for, you might need lots more features and lots more examples and then in that case sort of using a somewhat bigger brush, but still using these underlying principles of thinking about what's in your training set and trying to keep it balanced
across images and across visual appearances. Those are still good principles but maybe you can use a little bit of a bigger brush.
But keeping the principles of how random force work in mind will still tell you to do the least annotation that you can get away with, because your model will be faster and it will be easier to retrain if you realize that there's something that it didn't account for later, which is often what happens.
You know, you did it on batch one now you want to bring in data from batch two batch two is a little different. Do you want to spend the same three hours you spent in batch one or you don't spend the same 10 minutes you spent in batch one.
Love it. Yeah. All right, so that was the rule there was a rat a reason behind madness. Hopefully this helps you understand random force better in general and also why we are so obsessed with ilastiks tiny as brass.
I love it. And I certainly have a much stronger intuition about random forests now.
You know, I have always followed the rule because from my very first day in the lab that you know like the rule was made clear. This is the rule you follow but pretty nice to be able to develop the intuition behind you know what is actually going on in, you know, the math behind the curtain.
To understand why we are following this rule.
All right. Thank you so much. Have a wonderful day. I appreciate you hanging out with me while I do math simulations.
Of course. Thank you so much. This is this is delightful and you know it's it is always nice to know why we're following certain roles. So this is great. Thanks dear.
Yeah.